<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A reply by T.W. citizen of Chester, to a Vindication of Mr. M.H's Brief enquiry into the true nature of schism, from the exceptions of T.W. &amp;c. By a person who conceals his name</title>
            <author>T.W. citizen of Chester.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 147 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A65399</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W128</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R219277</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99830767</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99830767</idno>
            <idno type="VID">35221</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A65399)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 35221)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1878:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A reply by T.W. citizen of Chester, to a Vindication of Mr. M.H's Brief enquiry into the true nature of schism, from the exceptions of T.W. &amp;c. By a person who conceals his name</title>
                  <author>T.W. citizen of Chester.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Quire E appears to have been imposed incorrectly; pages 38-39 precede pages 36-37, which precede pages 34-35.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Henry, Matthew, 1662-1714. --  Brief enquiry into the true nature of schism --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Tong, William, 1662-1727. --  Vindication of Mr. M.H's Brief enquiry into the true nature of schism.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35221:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A REPLY By <hi>T. W.</hi> Citizen of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> To a VINDICATION of Mr. <hi>M. H's</hi> Brief Enquiry into the true Nature of Schiſm, from the Exceptions of <hi>T. W.</hi> &amp;c. By a Perſon who conceals his Name.</head>
            <p>THE <hi>Prince of Peace</hi> Bleſſed for ever, laid this Command upon his Diſciples, <hi>Mark</hi> 9. v. 50. <hi>Have Peace one with another;</hi> and that this Command might have the deeper impreſſion in their minds, he left it as his Legacy, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14 v. 27. <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you;</hi> how numerous ſoever they might in all Succeeding Ages come to be, this was to be the Badge and Character by which his Diſciples were to be known to the world, and to one another: now whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that in any Caſe violates this Command, and ſets at naught this Legacy, is no longer a Diſciple of the Holy Jeſus the Prince of Peace, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he repent and return.</p>
            <p>Yet notwithſtanding all this, there has ſcarce any Age ſince the Church of Chriſt had a being, been free from ſome or other, who have pretended to be the Diſciples of Chriſt in an extraordinary manner, and yet have had no regard to this holy Command, nor any value or eſteem for this Sacred Legacy.</p>
            <p>For they are moſt notoriouſly Guilty of breaking this Law, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning this Legacy, who revile and oppoſe that Government of the Church which was inſtituted by our Bleſſed Saviour; founded in his Apoſtles, and convey'd by them to their Succeſſors, and ſo has continued in a right Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion
<pb facs="tcp:35221:2"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35221:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:35221:3"/>
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:35221:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:35221:4"/>to this preſent time; of this ſort our Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> are, and ſome or ot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r of them, are frequently putting out Pamphlets wherein they endeavour to acquit themſelves of this great Crime by Juſtifying their Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration from the Government of the Church.</p>
            <p>To this purpoſe Mr. <hi>M. H—ry</hi> Printed a Pamphlet the laſt year, which he called, <hi>a brief Enquiry into the true Nature of Schiſm;</hi> there was not much more of the Nature of Schiſm, than of the Philoſophers Stone in it; however the not Anſwering it gave it the more Credit, and ſwell'd his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples with Triumph, ſo as ſome of them boaſted in my hearing, that it could not be anſwered by any Clergy-man; this made me uneaſie, and conſidering how unſuitable it was to any Clergy-man to concern himſelf with it, and withal conſidering, that this might be an Argument to proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite the weak and more unſtable people. I under took it in hopes that the Catholic truths laid down (thô by ſo mean and weak a hand) might put a ſtop to their boaſting, and it had theſe effects: Firſt, few believed but that it was done by ſome Clergy-man who prevail'd with me, to print it in my name. And ſecondly, that Mr. <hi>M H—ry</hi> for all the fulneſs of Gifts his Diſciples boaſted to be in him, thought as I may reaſonably (from his calling in aid) ſuppoſe it was above his Talent to meddle with.</p>
            <p>Now leſt the neglect of a Reply ſhould be fatal to them, and ſtagger their blind Proſelytes in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> and parts adjacent; they ſought and found out a man of great Size to attack me, a choſen Veſſel, one of the Firſt rate, who has fired all his Guns at me, and ſhot a great deal of Venom, and little elſe, which I hope in this following Paper ſhall make to appear.</p>
            <p>This great man conceals his Name, and perhaps not without good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. In the front of his Book he tells us, <hi>That man muſt be a great ſtranger in</hi> England, <hi>who knows not what unhappy Fl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mes have been kindled among us about matters of Church Government and W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rſhip; and he muſt be as great an Enemy that would not contribute his utmoſt to the extinguiſhing of them; a great deal has been writ on both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to convince the world where the fault of our Diviſion lies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the <hi>Government of the Church</hi> by Epiſcopacy was of Apoſtolic Inſtitution and Ordination is evident,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Government of the Church by Epi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>copacy is of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ivine Inſtitution.</note> for that <hi>Timothy</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi> of <hi>Crete</hi> by Apoſtolical Ordination and Inſtitution, is very clear in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Epiſtles to them both. That the ſeven Ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ies in <hi>Aſia</hi> which received the Chriſtian Faith, had each City a Biſhop, in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ident by the Title St. <hi>John</hi> gives an his Letters to them, contain'd in the Second and Third Chapters in the <hi>Revelations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that after the Apoſtles time, wherever the Chriſtian Faith was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:35221:4"/>in the early Ages of Chriſtianity, this <hi>Government</hi> was ſet over them, and that then all Chriſtians own'd and ſubmitted to this <hi>Government,</hi> is ſufficiently proved by the concurrent Teſtimonies of all the Fathers in thoſe Primitive times, and from thoſe times this Government received no inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, nor was at any time controverted or queſtioned, except by <hi>Aerius, Iſchyras,</hi> and one or two more, (who were condemned for Schiſmaticks) till the laſt Age, and then by this ſort of Men, by ſetting up a new miſtaken Notion of <hi>Parochial and Congregational Epiſcopacy</hi> with Lay Elders, to ſhare in the <hi>Government of the Church,</hi> never heard of before.</p>
            <p>To <hi>Church Government</hi> diſputed, he adds <hi>Worſhip,</hi> (by which I ſuppoſe he means the Worſhip of God) which chiefly conſiſts, of the unfeigned belief of the Articles of Faith deliver'd by the Apoſtles; the Offering up Prayers, Interceſſions,<note place="margin">The Worſhip of God in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ure as in any other Church whatſoever.</note> Thankſgiving and Praiſes unto God Almighty, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Will declared in the Holy Scripture; preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the name of his Son, Chriſt Jeſus, with all Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Humility and Geſtures expreſſing the ſame, the word of God read and duly and truly preach'd; the holy Sacraments <hi>Babtiſm</hi> and the <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt</hi> rightly and duly adminiſtred.</p>
            <p>Now all this is done with as much Reverence and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ravity, Simplicity and Goſpel purity in the Church of <hi>England</hi> as in any Church whatſoever; own'd to be ſo, and highly honored and eſteem'd for it, among all the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Churches, except thoſe men of Violence, your Brethren of the Kirk of <hi>Scotland,</hi> with whom we have nothing to do, only to pray for them.</p>
            <p>They of <hi>Rome</hi> indeed,<note place="margin">Diſſenters kindled, the flames of Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> were the only men who firſt oppos'd the reformed Worſhip of our Church; purified and cleanſed from their Innovations and Corruptions as it ſtands eſtabliſhed both by Canon and Statute Laws; and theſe Diſſenters have purſued Their Game, and in this made themſelves Their Partners by continuing and increaſing thoſe Flames to this day, not without hopes to compleat what the Papiſt ſo much endeavoured, and ſtill with theſe men earneſtly deſire, <hi>viz.</hi> the overturning and ſuppreſſing of this reformed Worſhip. So the Flames were kindled by the Papiſts firſt, and then by theſe men, by their Diſputing and Arraigning the Eſtabliſhed Worſhip.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Church Government</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> being thus ſtated, it eaſily ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears, that the Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> are they who <hi>kindled the unhappy flames</hi> (this Gent. talks of) among us. Now let us ſee how they may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed, where the fault lies?</hi> and who are the <hi>Enemies that will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute their utmoſt to quench them?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Men who are not mad, will go far for Water to quench thoſe Flame;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:35221:5"/>which elſe would deſtroy their dwellings,<note place="margin">They will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute to quench them.</note> but theſe men need go no farther but do their duty and the <hi>flames</hi> are out. To diſobey the Orders of our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, is to tranſgreſs a plain Law of God. If theſe men have any thing impoſed on them by our Governors that is ſinful let them ſhew it, and their Plea muſt be allow'd, but they are forced to confeſs the Terms of Obedience impoſ'd, are but <hi>indifferent things, mere trifles;</hi> Now for a man to diſobey his Governors and have no other plea but this, it is too mean to excuſe him from the tranſgreſſion of a known Law. Obey them that have the Rule over you is the command of the holy Apoſtle.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> Nor can <hi>indiffernt things,</hi> or what they acknowledg, <hi>mere trifles,</hi> be a pretence ſufficient to bind the Conſcience, againſt an expreſs Law of God, for as if the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle had foreſeen theſe mens Plea; he Commands Obedience to our Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors for Conſcience ſake, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.5. I hope by what is ſaid, it will be allowed by all impartial men, and ſound Chriſtians, that I may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude without breach of Charity, that the Diſſenters in <hi>England,</hi> are they who <hi>kindle the unhappy Flames about Church Government and Worſhip,</hi> and that they are <hi>the great Enemies that will not contribute the leaſt</hi> (not ſo much as do their Duty) <hi>to quench them;</hi> and that (notwithſtanding all the Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he talks of) <hi>the fault of all our Diviſions lies</hi> at their door.</p>
            <p>He goes on; <hi>The word Schiſm has been toſs'd like a Tennis-ball, from one ſide to another, till by ſuch motion thoſe violent heats have been cauſed that have much endangered both our Church and State.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this Rhetoric I ſuppoſe is meant the Oppoſition and Diſputes made by theſe men againſt the eſtabliſhed Church of <hi>England;</hi> that by theſe means, theſe men not only <hi>endangered,</hi> but for ſome years involved both <hi>Church and State</hi> in Ruin and Deſolation; had I brought no arguments, yet by ſad experience is ſufficiently proved.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>Great endeavours have been uſed to faſten the Guilt upon ſuch as impoſe unneceſſary and ſuſpected Terms of Communion, and it has been is fur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ly retorted upon thoſe who comply not with thoſe Terms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here the Terms of Communion are <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary and Suſpected</hi> (only;) but who are to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Judges of what things are neceſſary, or what <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary,</hi> they that bear Rule over us, or they that owe Subjection? Government always implies Subjection; and how can bare ſuſpicion diſcharge a man from the dury of Obedience? This is certain, that if a Father command his Son to do ſomething which is in it ſelf not Unlawful, and if the Son tell his Father it is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary,</hi> and that he <hi>Suſpects</hi> it to be ſo, and if only for that Reaſon will not obey, that Son is a Tranſgreſſor againſt the fifth Commandment; and its as certain that this is truly applicable to theſe men; all their Expoſiters affirm, that Obedience to their lawful Rulers &amp;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:35221:5"/>Paſtors, is required by that Commandment. But becauſe the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie which theſe Diſſenters, have againſt our Church mainly depends on theſe two perticulars mentioned by this Gent. viz. <hi>Church Government and Worſhip,</hi> it will be very neceſſary to lay down ſome irrefragable In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances to prove what was the Practice of the Church, in reſpect of its Government in the times next after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles;<note place="margin">Epiſcopacy the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church in the times next after the Apoſtles.</note> and this I do becauſe by referring thereto, I ſhall anſwer many paſſages which follow in this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Book.</p>
            <p>I begin with the Canon of the Apoſtles, which I find thus Tranſlated by a perſon of great worth, both for Learning and Veracity: <q>Let not the Presbyters or Deacons do any thing without the Conſent of the Biſhop, for he hath the people of the Lord intruſted to him, and there ſhall one day be required of him an account of their Souls.</q> Here the Biſhop has the Power of Governing the Presbyters and Deacons. Of what Authority theſe Canons are, <hi>Juſtellus</hi> has made evident, in his account of the Code of the Univerſal Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemens Romanus</hi> who was an Adjutor of the Apoſtles, and as <hi>Linus</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeden St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>Cletus Lanus,</hi> ſo he Succeeded <hi>Cletus</hi> in the Biſhopric of <hi>Rome,</hi> where all others in Holy Orders were called Presbyters, except Deacons only; who ſpeaking of the Apoſtles in his <hi>Ep. ad Corinth. p.</hi> 57. ſaith, <q>That they foreſeeing that there would be Contentions and Emula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about the Name or Dignity of Biſhop, or Epiſcopacy, they ſet down a Liſt or continuation of Succeſſors, that when any dyed, ſuch a certain perſon ſhould Succeed him.</q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignatius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Antioch</hi> and Martyr, who ſaw Jeſus and liv'd in the Apoſtles age, whoſe Authority many of later times, Enemies to Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, have oppoſed yet never could ſuppreſs the plainneſs of it. In his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Smyrneans,</hi> he ſaith, <q>But avoid Diviſions as the beginning of evils, and be all of you obſervant of the Biſhop, as Jeſus Chriſt was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant of the Father; and obſerve the Presbyters as the Apoſtles; and reverence the Deacons as the Command of God. Let no man preſume to do any thing in the Church without the Biſhop. And let that Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt only be accounted firm, which is either performed by the Biſhop him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or by his Licence. <hi>And a little further;</hi> He who honoreth the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop honoreth God; but he who doth any thing without the Biſhop's ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation, performs a Service to Satan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In his Epiſtle to the <hi>Epheſians:</hi> 
               <q>Therefore (purſuant to ſomething be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore) it becomes you every way to glorifie Jeſus Chriſt who glorifies you, that being perfected and knit up in the ſame Subjection, and being of one
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:35221:6"/>mind, and of one judgment, you may all ſpeak the ſame things, and being Subject to the Biſhop, (which <hi>Oneſimus</hi> then was) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, may be Sanctify'd in all things.</q> Again in the ſame Epiſtle, <q>As Jeſus Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> who is our into uparable life did follow the judgment of the Father; and the Biſhops who are deſigned to the ends of the Earth, follow the judgment of Jeſus Chriſt; therefore it is a comely thing for you to concur in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ment of the Biſhop, as alſo you do; for your Presbyters moſt worthy of Praiſe and of God, is ſo adapted to the Biſhop, as ſtrings are fitted to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rp, inſomuch that Jeſus Chriſt is Celebrated through your unanimity and agreement in Love. And in the ſame Ep. Therefore let us endeavour to be in ſubjection to the Biſhops, that we may be Gods Subjects.</q>
            </p>
            <p>In his Epiſtle to the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> 
               <q>For I was accounted worthy to ſee <hi>Dam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s</hi> your Divite <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>op and the worthy Presbyters <hi>Baſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Apolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n</hi> the Deacon, my Fellow-ſervant, whom I would enjoy, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſubject to the Biſhop as to the Grace of God, and to the Presbyters as to the Law of Jeſus Chriſt.</q> A little further he ſaith; <q>For ſome in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eed there are, who own the Biſhop in name, but do all things without him: ſuch men appear to me, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e men of no good Conference, becauſe they hold Meetings not eſtabliſhed by Commandment, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I could heap up many more Inſtances, but that would be tedious; I will therefore conclude with the Council of <hi>I aodicea, Can.</hi> 55. which I find by an eminent Doctor in our Church, thus Tranſlated. <hi>The Presbyters muſt do nothing without the Conſent of the Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That the Authority I have brought to prove, that the ancient Goverment of the Chriſtian Church was by Biſhops and (that it was an Order Superior and had power of Juriſdiction over the Presbyters and Deacons) ſhould be undeniably and firmly receiv'd and Submitted to, by all Chriſtians, I offer theſe Reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Firſt,</hi> It was this ſame Authority which gather'd all the writings of the Evangeliſts and Apoſtles, and declar'd them to be the word of God, the dictates of the Holy Ghoſt, and all Chriſtians have ſo receiv'd them and do hold them to be Canonical and uſe them and reverence them as ſuch to this very day.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It was by the ſame Authority, that the firſt day of the week was De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to be the Lords Day (there being no Precept Commanding it in Scripture) and all Chriſtians have yeilded Obedience to it, and do ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part that Day to Celebrate the Worſhip of God in a moſt Solemn manner as if Commanded by Holy Scripture.</p>
            <p n="3">3 And laſtly, this Authority of the Ancient Fathers and firſt General
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:35221:6"/>Councils, which affirm the Government of the Church to be Epiſcopacy, is one great means by which the Pious and Learned Divines of our Church (if this Gent. will give me leave to call 'em ſo) have clearly evinced and diſcoverd the Innovations and Corruptions impoſed by the Church of Rome on all in her Communion, to be fictitious and no way agreeing with the practice of the Primitive Church.</p>
            <p>Now if upon the Authority of the Primitive Fathers and Councils, Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience was univerſally given to acknowledge and receive the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as the Word of God; and the Lords day celebrated as if command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Divine Precept, which is infallibly true; Is it reaſonable now, to diſpute their Writings and Decrees, their practice and uſage, concerning the nature of the Government of the Church, which they were fully aſſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed was eſtabliſhed by the Apoſtles themſelves?</p>
            <p>And now I return to wait upon this unknown Gentleman. In his 2. p. he ſays, <hi>Some have fancied the ſevere Execution of Penal Laws, by Fines, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, Exile,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>would have put an end to that Separation,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>but Experience hath convinced them of a quite contrary effect.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gent. will carry all before him if credited; I could certainly procure a Certificate under ſome hundreds of Hands of very Honeſt and Good men in <hi>Cheſter,</hi> that the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> when executed there, had brought all the Presbyterians, except a very ſmall inconſiderable number to Conformity; ay, and one of the oldeſt and ſtouteſt of them, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to the Rector of the Pariſh he liv'd in, that he, <hi>viz.</hi> the Rector had ſo throughly ſatisfied him, that he did not partake at the Euchariſt out of fear of the <hi>Law,</hi> but for the ſatisfaction of his Conſcience, and that he would continue to do ſo; but no ſooner came the Indulgence out, but this old Puritan, and pretended Convert, ſet the Church at defiance, and with many more of that Tribe returned to their <hi>Separation;</hi> and thus it was ſaid to be in moſt part of <hi>England;</hi> it's certain, that had not that Indulgence come out in King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second's time, which was procured by the Duke of <hi>York</hi> for ſome ſpecial Service deſigned by him for the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Church, there had been but a few in Conventicles, except Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Quakers, who are incorri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le and above all others hardned, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt beyond hope; and yet this Gent. ſo confidently affirms, <hi>that the Penal I a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s by experience had a quite contrary Eſpect,</hi> which is much more bold than true. In his 2 pag. he ſays further, <hi>Others have perſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aded themſelves when ever ſuch enforcements were laid <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>e, the controverted Ceremonies would of courſe fall into Contempt, for being (by acknowledgment) things purely indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>without any native worth or ſtrength, they cannot be rationally ſuppoſed to ſtand any longer than they had thoſe external props to bear them up;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:35221:7"/>And er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in they have not been altogether diſapo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nted, for they hear of five or ſix of the Clergy, and thoſe not of the me <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt ſort, that have ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſen to quit their preſerments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> eaſe of their Conſciences,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> (he ſays) <hi>ſome had,</hi> I ſhall again oppoſe matter of Fact; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> times of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rpa ſon which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed more than Twelve years, all which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s were laid and, and the external props were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and yet even <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en, the far greater <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the beſt peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> perſevere in their Affection and Communion with the Church of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> man are the great care taken by the then Rulers; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Parliament (as then call'd) required, that no perſon ſhould have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Book found in Cuſtody, upon pain of being Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> at the pleaſure of the then Judges, who were their implacable Enemies (here the <hi>Enforcements</hi> were thought neceſſary on the other fide) and the vaſt numbers of theſe who retain'd Communion with the Church, (notwithſtanding the Enforcements to the contrary) appear'd with hearts full of Joy and Gratitude upon the Reſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ration.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Five or Six of the Cler<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who he ſays are gone from us and are <hi>none of the meaniſt,</hi> I know not who he means; had they been Eminent men we ſhould have heard of 'em; this is trifling, or I can tell him of Dr. <hi>Dillingh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m</hi> Vice Chancellor, Dr. <hi>Connant</hi> Rector of <hi>Exeter</hi> Colledge, Vice Chancellor and Regis Proteſſor of Divinity, and many more (thô he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps is aſham'd to name our Diſerters) of th'other party, who Conform'd notwithſtanding the Indulgence.</p>
            <p>In p. 3. he ſaith, <hi>That ſince neither Diſputing nor Penal Laws have hitherto brought</hi> Engliſh <hi>Proteſtants to an exact <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity, it is worth every honeſt mans Enquiry how under theſe different Modes of Worſhip, all men may be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to live quiet and peaceable lives,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The Apoſtles Rule is, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 10. <hi>Now I beſeech you Brethren, in the name of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all ſpeak the ſame things, and that there be no Diviſions among you: different M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>des of Worſhip</hi> are here forbidden, <hi>and an exact <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity</hi> in the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> requir'd, and I hope that this Gent. will not deny that this Rule is in force in the Church of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> lan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> and if this Gent. would preſs this Doctrin, he needs not puzzle men with any farther <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ry</hi> how they may be <hi>induc'd to live quiet and peaceable lives.</hi> And I preſume here to tell him, that againſt ſuch who will not <hi>live quiet and peaceable lives,</hi> there are <hi>Penal Laws</hi> ſtill in force. And this anſwers his next Paragraph, where he gives his Brother Mr. <hi>H—ry</hi> high Encomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums <hi>for his very modeſt and ingenious attempt,</hi> in his Book of <hi>the Nature of Schiſm,</hi> notwithſtanding which, it doth appear that <hi>the Wars and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> irretated by them againſt the Church <hi>proceed from</hi> their <hi>Luſts,</hi> which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:35221:7"/>
               <hi>would</hi> be at an end, where they <hi>entirely ſubject to Reaſon and Virtue, as the Goſpel requires.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In p. 4. this Gent. would induce us to believe, that he is well skill'd in ſome ſtrange Art, for he ſays, that I am <hi>a furious Zealot and a Debauchee,</hi> and that he knows by the <hi>Complexion of my Book.</hi> This Gent. may take the Liberty to cenſure me for a <hi>furious Zealot,</hi> becauſe I have in my former paper affirm'd the Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> to be Schiſmatics; I do with the poor Publican cry, <hi>God be merciful to me a Sinner;</hi> but there's not an <hi>jota</hi> in that paper wich in the leaſt tends to <hi>Debauchery.</hi> In p. 5. he's very angry that I give the Titles of <hi>Pious and Learned</hi> to our Epiſcopal Clergy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he ſays, that I call the <hi>Diſſenters Fools and Schiſmaties,</hi> and is at a great Expence of Rhetoric upon me for theſe.</p>
            <p>I cannot mention our Epiſcopal Clergy without Reverence; they are the <hi>Stewards of the manifold Myſteries of God, and Miniſters of Reconciliation;</hi> and thô my calling them by thoſe Titles contributes not a mite to their worth, yet it was my duty to give the Titles due to them, eſpecially in a paper I intended to Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>liſh. I ſaid (indeed) the Folly and Schiſm of our Diſſenters has been clearly evinced, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is an ordinary way in ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to joyn the word Folly with a Crime, and ſo by Folly and Schiſm I intended no more than the Folly of Schiſm, one act of Folly denominates not a <hi>Fool;</hi> but if this Gent. will miſconſtrue and pervert my Words, and thereby proclaim himſelf and his fellow Diſſenters <hi>Fools</hi> as well as <hi>Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tics</hi> it is out of my Power to help; indeed theſe are not worth a mans no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice, only to ſhew, that this Gentlemans temper is too peeviſh for the Goſpel, who at ſuch little things ſo cauſlesſly takes an occaſion to cavil.</p>
            <p>The next thing he quarels at, is in p. 6. That <hi>I muſter againſt them the great names of</hi> Hooker, Bramhal, Sanderſon, <hi>and diverſe others, and won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders why</hi> Parker, Dryden, <hi>and</hi> L'Strange <hi>with their Learned and Elaborate Writings ſhould not come in for a ſhare of honor with them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir, <hi>Hooker</hi> and the others I named; for Piety and Learning are honor'd all the world over, and your detraction and all the Art you have, cannot leſſen 'em. But Sr. as for <hi>Parker, Dryden,</hi> and <hi>L'Strange,</hi> who you nam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to <hi>ſhare with them in that Honor,</hi> there can be no reaſon; They ſtand faireſt for your Kalendar; I had been a Criminal ſhould I have robb'd you of 'em, for they joyned hands with you in your Addreſſes to King <hi>James</hi> the 2d. to Congratulate and Applaud his Excellent Government, in grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> and they readily conſented with you to the taking oft the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and <hi>Teſt,</hi> and in allowing the <hi>Diſpenſing Power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here I think a proper place to anſwer what you ſay, in the beginning of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:35221:8"/>your 6. p. where you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> france ſome words of mine, and ſay, <hi>They have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Terms, to do the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rk of a common <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oe, in ruining thoſe that were more early aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e of the adva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ces of Popiſh Deſigns then ſome of their Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bors,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Sr. by this word <hi>Neighbors.</hi> I apprehend (and that truly) that you mean they of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> Why! they were the men who in time of extremity and danger, oppoſed the <hi>advances of Popery,</hi> and with Si<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y and Courage ſtood in the Gap; and this they did in two reſpects, Firſt by reſuſing to take off the <hi>Penal Laws</hi> and the <hi>Teſt,</hi> and diſowning the <hi>Diſpenſing Power. <hi>The Penal Laws,</hi>
               </hi> which by God's good Providence, were raiſed as a Fence to preſerve us from Popery being about to be laid waſt, and <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> without exception already granted, (an<note n="‖" place="margin">Witneſs your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes.</note> Artifice by which moſt if not all your Party were gull'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d cheated into a compliance with the times) The Arch-biſhop of <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>terbury,</hi> with ſix more Biſhops, induced from a deep ſenſe they had of a Deſign then viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to bring in Popery, from a holy Zeal, and a deep ſenſe they had of their Duty, to preſerve the Church from the ſad effects of that Deſign, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented their Petition to the King, declaring their readineſs to have tender Conſciences conſidered, ſo it might be done in a Parliamentary way; but for their Non-compliance with the <hi>Diſpenceing power,</hi> and thoſe other things, wherein you ſo readily comply'd, by which you very much <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted the advances of Popery;</hi> they were all made Priſoners in the Tower, which ſuffering of theirs, God bleſſed with a very happy event. And Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly they of the Church of <hi>England</hi> put a ſtop to the <hi>advances of Potery,</hi> by their Induſtrious and Learned Writings againſt Papiſts; a Popiſh Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet from the <hi>Savoy</hi> or <hi>Wild-houſe,</hi> in thoſe days could ſcarce be dry, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t ſome or other Learned Divine of our Church, ſtopt its Carrier with ſuch anſwers as ſilenced and ſhamed them; ſtrengthened the weak and ſtag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, recalled many, and gave joy and ſatisfaction to all the Members of the Church in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>al.</p>
            <p>My Author ſays in p. 6. <hi>But if we thought ſit to imitate his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> (meaning my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ming <hi>Hooker,</hi> &amp;c.) <hi>we could t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll him of</hi> Reynals, C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>it<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ndel, Ames, Daille, Owen, Baxter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (ay, and <hi>John</hi> a <hi>Leyd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n</hi> too)</p>
            <p>This Gent. condemns me of <hi>Pedentry,</hi> yet his Gravity imitates me in the next breath even in that. The firſt he names, is <hi>Reynalds,</hi> he (alaſs) was ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſible of their Schiſm, ſhook<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ands with 'em and dyed an eminent mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of our Church. <hi>Cartwright</hi> was contemporary with Mr. Hooker, and let all Sober minded men Judge if the Eccleſiaſtical Politie Writ by Mr. <hi>Hooker,</hi> has not out-weighed by far, not only <hi>Cartwright,</hi> but all other
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:35221:8"/>Diſsenters who have written any thing of the Rites and Ceremonies and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verment of the Church; So has Dr. Hammond, Dr. Stillingfleet and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others againſt <hi>Owen, Baxter</hi> and the reſt of that Gang. I muſt beg his pardon that I can have no good opinion of<note n="‖" place="margin">Owen <hi>and</hi> Baxter.</note> ſuch who have ſpent their time and ſtudy to break the Order, Peace and Unity of the Church.</p>
            <p>His firſt Paragraph contains the whole Controverſy; I therefore thought it neceſſary to give that a full anſwer: So I have endeavoured to all his reflections that follow'd hitherto, but all he ſays to the remainder of my Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face, is either ſuch mere Droll or Cavil and ſo foreign to the Controverſy, that it is not worth paper to anſwer: I therfore now conſider what he ſays to my Anſwer.</p>
            <p>In his 9. <hi>pa.</hi> He ſays, I blame <hi>Mr H—ry for not chooſing the true Stan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dard whereby to diſco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>er Schiſm;</hi> He ſays Mr. H—ry <hi>choſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> other but the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing the great Law for the Government of men, and muſt certa <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>be the trueſt Touch ſtone of Sin and Duty, &amp;c.</hi> He ſays further; <hi>this is a hopeful begining of Controverſy to decline the Sufficiency and Propriety of Scripture as the Standard of good or evil. But will this man aſſigne a better? Yes</hi> (the <hi>IXth</hi> Article of the Apoſtles Creed, <hi>I Believe the Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church, the Communion of Saints</hi>) &amp;c. and concludes, <hi>a happy Omen, when the firſt Paragraph contains a plain affront both to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and common Senſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sr. the holy Scriptures is the <hi>great Law for the Government of men,</hi> and is certainly <hi>the trueſt Touch ſtone of Sin and Duty.</hi> But Sr. whoever he be,<note place="margin">Scripture ought not to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted contrary to an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith.</note> that expounds H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y Scripture in contradiction or not conſonant to an Article of Faith, his expoſition cannot be true, and I am aſſured ſo, by that Article of Faith it contradicts or agrees not with. As for example; the <hi>Socinians</hi> have with ſo much cunning and plauſibility expounded even thoſe texts of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which are expreſs for the Divinity of our Bleſſed Savior, in favour of their Hereſy, that they have ſtaggar'd and perverted many perſons of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable underſtanding; but when the Article of Faith is conſider'd, <hi>viz. And I Believe in one Lord Jeſus Chriſt the only begotten Son of God</hi> &amp; <hi>God of God, very God of very God, being of one Subſtance with the Father,</hi> &amp;c. every Chriſtian is infalliably aſſured that the Expoſition of the Sacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture made by the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inians</hi> are falſe, becauſe it is in contradiction to an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of Faith. So when I ſaw Mr. H—ry had expounded the holy Apoſtl's Precept <hi>I beſeech you Bretheren</hi> &amp;c. 1 Cor. 1.10. <hi>that there be no Diviſions among you</hi> &amp;c. and other Texts of Scripture, in favor of your Separat Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion to acquit that from the guilt of Schiſm, I was firmly aſſured that his Expoſitions were falſe, becauſe they claſh'd and agreed not with that <hi>IXth</hi> Article of Faith <hi>I Believe the <hi>Haly Catholic Church</hi>
               </hi> the <hi>Communion
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:35221:9"/>of Saints;</hi> a Separate Communion being altogether inconſiſtent with that Article of Faith: I therfore recomended that Article of Faith as a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and more eaſie way for him to find out the true nature of Schiſm, than his ſo unskilful expounding Scripture, which the Apoſtle ſaith 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1 20 <hi>is not of any Pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Interpretation.</hi> Sr. I know not who, nor what you are, but I muſt tell you, that to affirm that an Article of Faith is <hi>a plain affront to Scripture</hi> is the neareſt to the language of an Heretic that I have met with.</p>
            <p>In p. 10 he ſaith, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer to their Conſideration, the Origination or firſt Exiſtence of the Catholic Church, and that I ſaid it was before the day of Pentecoſt; but he ſays, <hi>how long before that day</hi> I tell 'em not, and then he takes an occaſion to let us know that he has read of the <hi>Babiloniſh Captivity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I did ſet down the Text, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. <hi>The number of the Names together were about an hundred and twenty,</hi> which was ſufficient to denote the time, and he owns that he knows my meaning; but to exerciſe his abundant wit, he ſays, <hi>here is a Diſcovery worthy of its Author;</hi> no body can think that I mention'd it as the <hi>Diſcoverer,</hi> but as neceſſarily previous to what follow'd. <hi>But</hi> (he ſays) <hi>had God no Churche<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> then among the</hi> Jews? <hi>muſt they be Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated too? for what cauſe pray?</hi> (and then reproachfully anſwers) <hi>Not for want of Ceremonies, or a Pontiff I hope.</hi> Then he ſays, <hi>the man told us in his Preface, the Angels in Heaven were the moſt Glorious Members of the Church. How muſt we lay theſe things together? were the Angels Originated at the day of Pentecoſt? Had they their firſt Exiſtence then? Or did the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Body Exiſt before the Body? Let the Citizen, or any other of his Cabal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſolve theſe Riddles, and he ſhall be my great</hi> Apollo.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God had</hi> a <hi>Church</hi> from the beginning of the World,<note place="margin">Church not call'd Catholic before the day of Pentecoſt. Pſal. <hi>2.8.</hi> Eph. <hi>2.14.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels in Heaven were</hi> from their Exiſtence <hi>Members</hi> of it, being Created for that end; an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Church of the Jews</hi> was Gods peculiar Church, are all infallibly true; but untill the Promiſe was fulfilled. <hi>Deſire of me, and I ſhall give thee the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eathen for thine Inheritance, and the utmoſt parts of the Earth for thy Poſſeſſion:</hi> Untill <hi>the middle Wall of the Partition was broken down</hi> (which was not 'til the Church was changed from Judaiſm to Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity) the Title <hi>Catholic,</hi> was never, nor could properly be attributed to the Church; now unleſs this Gent. will ſhew, that the Church was call'd Catholic before the <hi>Day of Pentecoſt</hi> I mentioned, all theſe Riddles and Philoſophical queſtions are of no more worth and value, than his great <hi>promiſe to make me his great</hi> Apollo.</p>
            <p>In p. 11. he queſtions not, that <hi>the Apoſtles and Diſciples were the Church nor the power Chriſt gave the Apoſtles to Preach the Goſpel to all the World;</hi> and ſays <hi>that I well obſerve Chriſt's Commiſſion and Charge, that in every Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian they that believed might be Baptiz'd and made Members of the Church?</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:35221:9"/>(but ſays he) <hi>how well they have obſerved their Commiſſion who refuſe to admit of Church Members upon their profeſſion of Faith, unleſs they will alſo comply with ſome ſignificant Rites of their own, that are alien to Scripture Rules,</hi> &amp;c. and then in his 12 p. he ſays, <hi>its plain from this mans Confeſſion, that to be a Diſciple or Believer, would make a man a Member of the Church in Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal times,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>It is true that <hi>Faith</hi> is the neceſſary Qualification of a mans admiſſion to Baptiſm, and that perſons are thereby made viſible Members of the Church,<note place="margin">Members of the Church to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Peace &amp; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in the Church.</note> but this is but the Initiation or beginning of Chriſtianity; Obedience to Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Rulers and Governors, being in this always ſuppos'd and imp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y'd; to <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Baptiſm</hi> muſt be added a ſtrict Obſervation of the Order, Peace and Unity of that holy Society into which they are admitted by thoſe Qualifications above mention'd; and this is moſt ſtrictly enjoyned by the Holy Jeſus, the Prince of Peace, and God of Order in the words mentioned in the beginning of this paper, and divers other Texts in Scripture. As for calling them <hi>Rites and Ceremonies of their own, that are alien to Scripture Rules,</hi> what ever tends to Order and the Beauty of Uniformity in the Church, is in the Power and Wiſdom of the Apoſtles Succeſſors, the Biſhops, to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, thô not expreſs'd in Scripture; there are no expreſs terms in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture for Infant Baptiſm, nor for Women to pertake at the Euchariſt, yet allowed and required by the Authority of the Church, and ſubmitted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to from the Primitive times by all Chriſtians, except Anabaptiſts, who de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the former. And this fully anſwers his following Paragraph, which he cloſeth with much bitterneſs and venom againſt our Clergy, and ſerves only to ſhew what Spirit he is of.</p>
            <p>In p. 13. he ſaith, <hi>But though the Apoſtles did propagate the Goſpel far and wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ie, yet that they did actually preach it to all Nations, is a thing we never beard of before</hi> T. W. <hi>told us ſo; and we muſt have better Evidence before we believe it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a mere Cavil, but he thinks he has ſufficiently ſhewed my naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;<note place="margin">The Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to all Nations.</note> I did not uſe the word <hi>Actually:</hi> I ſaid that according to our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viors Command the Apoſtles did Preach the Goſpel to all Nations; I could tell him out of very good Authoritys, the vaſt Countrys in the Roman Empire in which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>actually preach the Gospel</hi> and that St. <hi>James</hi> did ſo in the Regions of <hi>Paleſtine;</hi> St. <hi>Mark</hi> in <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries <hi>far</hi> about it, St. <hi>John</hi> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> St. <hi>Andrew</hi> in <hi>Achaja,</hi> St <hi>Thomas</hi> in <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> and of the other Apoſtles <hi>Propagating the Goſpel</hi> in other Countrys, ay, and Ordained Biſhops and Presbyters in 'em too; But the Scripture ſaith, <hi>There were dweling at Jeruſalem Jews,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 2 5.</note> 
               <hi>devout men out of every Nation under Heaven;</hi> to theſe the <hi>Apoſtles preached the Goſple,</hi> ſo in this reſpect, what I
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:35221:10"/>ſaid is true; I had no great reaſon to fear that I had committed an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable Crime; and if upon the Evidence given in Scripture he <hi>will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it</hi> he is at his liberty.</p>
            <p>He goes on; <hi>Whither the Seaven Churches in Aſia had Seaven Biſhops Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiding over them, neither more nor leſs is a thing that no way affects our preſent Controverſy, nor can any thing be concluded from thence in favor of our Engliſh Prelacy; till the Pawer of theſe Biſhops, the extent of their Dioceſses, the Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of their under Officers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>be proved the ſame with ours,</hi> viz. <hi>or liable to the ſame exceptions,</hi> &amp;c. I underſtand not this laſt Sentence, <hi>or liable to the ſame exceptions,</hi> unleſs he would make the Primitive Church <hi>liable to the ſame exceptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That <hi>there were ſeven Biſhops</hi> is unqueſtionable, unleſs he will not give Credit to St. <hi>John's</hi> Teſtimony; that the <hi>extent of their Dioceſſes</hi> may in ſome meaſure be right eſtimated, it will be neceſſary to conſider, what this <hi>Aſia</hi> doth ſignifie, which Dr. <hi>Hammond</hi> deſcribes thus: <q>
                  <hi>Aſia</hi> here doth not ſignifie the fourth part in the Diviſion of the World, but in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Notion, known to Geographers; the <hi>Lydian</hi> or proconſular <hi>Aſia,</hi> thus the word is uſed, <hi>Acts</hi> 19.26. where St. <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to perſwade much People not only at <hi>Epheſus,</hi> but almoſt thrô all <hi>Aſia;</hi> now in this <hi>Aſia,</hi> as there were many Cities, ſo there were ſome Metropoles, Chief or Mother Cities, to each of which, the leſſer adjacent were ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate. Of this ſort the firſt was <hi>Epheſus,</hi> ſaith <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lpian, l. Obſerv</hi> D. <hi>de Off. Procons.</hi> Such again was <hi>Thiatira,</hi> ſaith <hi>Ptolemy, l. Geog. 1ſt. Cap.</hi> 2. Such was <hi>Phyladelphia,</hi> of the Province of the <hi>Lydians.</hi> Of the ſame Rank are <hi>Laodicea, Sardis, Smyrna,</hi> and <hi>Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>amus,</hi> affirmed by <hi>Pliny</hi> (<hi>Nat. Hiſt. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 29.) as Cities wherein the Roman Proconſuls reſiding, kept Courts for all the adjoyning Cities to reſort to; by which it appears that all the Seven Cities here named, were Metropoles, and accordingly under theſe Seven, all other Chriſtian Churches were contained. And it is evident in <hi>Ignatius</hi>'s time (which was not long after) that <hi>Magneſia,</hi> and <hi>Trallys,</hi> upon the Banks of <hi>Meander,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Stephanus Bizantius</hi>) being conſequently included in this <hi>Aſia,</hi> were Epiſcopal Churches, or Cities, <hi>Damas</hi> being Biſhop of one and <hi>Polybius</hi> of the other, and ſo ſubordinate to the Metropolitan of <hi>Epheſus.</hi> After this the Doctor Tranſlates out of <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ebius;</hi> part of which I here in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, <hi>(viz)</hi> Who can recount the multitudes of Aſſemblies in every Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty? Who can deſcribe the Confluxes to the Oratories, and the ſpacious Churches which they built from the foundations, not contenting them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the ancient Edifices?</q> To theſe I will add but two more inſtances
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:35221:10"/>viz. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and <hi>Rome:</hi> That the <hi>Seaven Churches in Aſia,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Each City in the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times but one Biſhop.</note> and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in Jeruſalem and Rome had each of them but one Biſhop, is the voice of all the Chriſtian world, except the ſmall number of your miſtaken per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion; and that each of theſe great and populous Cities contained very many Congregations nothing can be more evident; and further, that it was impoſſible that all the many Congregations in each City could be Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred unto, by one Biſhop without the aſſiſtance of Presbyters: And now lay all this together,<note place="margin">Engliſh Prelacy the ſame with the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive.</note> and ſee if <hi>in favor of our Engliſh Prelacy</hi> every one is not forced to conclude, That the <hi>Prelacy</hi> or Dioceſan Biſhops in <hi>England</hi> is an exact paralel to the Churches above mentioned? Primitive Churches; &amp; that nothing but Obſtinacy, Pride &amp; Intereſt can binde or hold my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary and his Bretheren any longer in that fond and groundleſs Opinion of <hi>Congregational or Parochial Epiſcopacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the Power wherwith our Prelates are inveſted, it is from Heaven; the Son of God to whom all Power in Heaven and Earth was committed,<note place="margin">Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy of Divine Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and perpetual. Mat. <hi>16.</hi> v. <hi>19.</hi> Joh. <hi>20.</hi> v. <hi>23.</hi> Ibid. v. <hi>21.</hi> Mat. <hi>28.</hi> v. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> firſt promiſed it to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and <hi>I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive thee the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven;</hi> afterwards he gave it actually to all the Apoſties; <hi>whoſoever ſins ye remit they are remitted unto them, and whoſoever ſins ye retain they are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained:</hi> this is call'd the <hi>power</hi> of the Keys of binding and looſing; the <hi>power</hi> of Ordaining and Governing is given in theſe words; <hi>as my Father ſent me, even ſo ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I you.</hi> And that this <hi>Power</hi> was to continue by Succeſſion until the ſecond coming of our Lord, is manifeſt in theſe words; <hi>and lo I am with you always even to the end of the World.</hi> And accordingly this <hi>Power</hi> has deſcended by Succeſſion from the Apoſtles to this preſent Age. Now here is <hi>Epiſcopacy both name and thing</hi> (as you call it) <hi>according to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Standard</hi> proved, which you ſeem to deſire; and now be not offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed nor angry that you are (as you term it) <hi>run down,</hi> which is, that your Erronious Opinion, contrary to all Antiquity is ſo plainly diſcovered, not (as you ſay) <hi>by a bare word only,</hi> but by moſt firm and undeniable Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</p>
            <p>The <hi>under Officers</hi> you mention, are own'd to be no other than of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential Inſtitution for diſpatch of buſineſs, but are eſtabliſhed by Law, to whom therefore your Obedience is due.</p>
            <p>I wonder you mention your <hi>Scotch Presbytery;</hi> it can be for no other purpoſe than as a Rod ſhaken at us to beware of you,<note place="margin">Scotch Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry a Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to us</note> for they have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently explained what is meant by <hi>Comprehention,</hi> to wit the expultion of Epiſcopacy, and have aſſur'd us that our Biſhops and Clergy, will meet with the ſame barbarous uſage here, if ever it come into your Power.</p>
            <p>In p. 14. he modeſtly ſays, <hi>he will not take upon him to contradict thoſe Learned men, who think the Angels</hi> (mentioned in the <hi>Revel.</hi> by St. <hi>John</hi>)
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:35221:11"/>
               <hi>were Biſhops;</hi> he having granted this, is all my deſire, and therefore all his witty Animadverſions which follow, are not worth my anſwering. It would be but needleſs Repetition to ſay any thing to his following Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph in his 14. p. having fully anſwered it before.</p>
            <p>In his p. 15. he ſays, <hi>What do I mean in ſaying in theſe Multiplyed Churches there was no Variation;</hi> and then very diſingenuouſly changes my word, for a word very different in ſignification, and asks, <hi>Was there no variety at all in any Circumſtance of Worſhip?</hi> and ſays, <hi>the contrary may be prov'd even in the Apoſtles times,</hi> and inſtances that which he calls <hi>a Scuffle, Acts</hi> 15. betwixt the believing Jews and Gentiles, about Jewiſh Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies.</p>
            <p>Here were no ſuch <hi>different Circumſtances</hi> as to divide their Communion, therein there was no <hi>Variation,</hi> their Unity was preſerved; the Jewiſh Ceremonies, which the Converted Jews would have impoſed on the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Gentiles were no <hi>Circumſtances</hi> in the Chriſtian Worſhip; the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil at <hi>Jeraſalem</hi> thought therefore neceſſary to forbid thoſe Impoſitions; now in this very Caſe the neceſſity of Apoſtolic Juriſdiction doth appear, that by a deciſive and definitive Sentence of Eccleſiaſtical Authority, it may not be in the power of private Chriſtians to impoſe their different Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents upon one another, and that there may be no <hi>Variation</hi> nor breach of Unity in the public Worſhip of God. So that this Inſtance is not at all for his purpoſe. He ſays if I mean, <hi>there was no variation from Scripture Rules (tho we are afraid that will ſcarce hold, yet) we wiſh it had been ſo ſtill.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Scripture Rules</hi> here, he certainly means the <hi>New Teſtament;</hi> if this Gent. had any regard to Eccleſiaſtical Antiquity, he would never have talked <hi>of Scripture</hi> (that is New T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ment) <hi>Rules</hi> before they were written.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>We have a Notion of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yed down</hi> (in my p. 2.) <hi>in which we freely concur with him;</hi> theſe are my words (for he has not tranſcribed them fairly) They are all one with that Church firſt mentioned at <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and (which he omits) all one with one another; being all United into one Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Society or Body, under one Head Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (and which he has omitted too) and are in all things the ſune with that firſt Church, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited in one Baptiſm, and one Faith, and all partakers at the ſame Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>That,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>is the ſame for ſubſtance, for in that they all agreed in the Primitive times, in the ſame Circumſtances ſuch a <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity we hold; and doubt not but in our Congregations this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity may be found.</hi> And ſo he runs on in his 16. p. and endeavours to perſwade all men (juſt like the Donatiſts) that theſe Diſſenters are more truly Catholic than we.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:35221:11"/>
            <p>That the <hi>Power</hi> delegated by our bleſſed Saviour to his Apoſtles was to be confer'd upon their Succeſſors, is certainly implyed in the promiſe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</note> 
               <hi>Lo I am with you alway, even to the end of the world.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Church of <hi>England</hi> truly A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical.</note> That the Church of <hi>England</hi> was Planted, either by ſome of the Apoſtles or ſome of their Succeſſors and that the Succeſſion of Biſhops has continued in this Church from that firſt propagation; by as ſtrong proofs as human Authority is ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of, <hi>viz.</hi> by Records and Hiſtories may appear; and conſequently that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is as truly an Apoſtolic and Catholic Church as <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem, Alexandria, Antioch</hi> and thoſe other Churches which were of the firſt Planting.</p>
            <p>Her Orders then are to be equally obeved, Her Unity and Peace as ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly mantained and whatſoever amounted to Schiſm in any of them muſt be ſo in her: your Uniting then in a Communion Separate from this Church, bears no ſimilitude with Primitive Unity, being contrary to their Practice. And being that in your <hi>Congregations</hi> the Divine Authority is wanting, there can be no ſuch Unity found among you, as Primitive Unity.</p>
            <p>He Says <hi>the Euchariſt was the ſame for Subſtance in the Primitive Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and that <hi>they all agreed in the ſame Circumſtances;</hi> It is very true, for no difference would be allow'd; Chriſtians then, durſt not entertain ſo wicked and uncharitable a thought, as that of ſetting up a Separate Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation as you do; They devoted themſelves to the Command of their maſter, <hi>to have Peace one with another.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mark</hi> 9.50. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.17.</note> They for Conſcience ſake obſerv'd the Command of the Apoſtle, <hi>Obey them that have the Rule over you;</hi> If you would tread in their ſteps, you would as Relgiouſly obſerve the Unity and Peace of the Eſtabliſhed Church wherein you live in all Circumſtances as they did.</p>
            <p>All his next Paragraph <hi>Pa.</hi> 17. is the ſame, in different Phraſes; He ſays, the deſcription <hi>I have given of Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity ruins my whole Book</hi> and <hi>Cauſe</hi> (an haſty Sentence) for ſays he, <hi>if this be the true proper <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, then there may be true Church-<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity without the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niting of many parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, Miniſters and People into one Dioceſan Church under the Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of a Prelate and his Officers</hi> &amp;c. Then he is not much againſt the <hi>conveniency of Parochial-Precincts,</hi> but ſays <hi>according to my Definition, it is not De eſſentia Vnitatis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is plain, all that he drives at here is that there may be true Church U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity without Epiſcopacy, I have anſwer'd this before by ſhewing, that all Preſbyters with their Particular Congregations, that is Miniſters and People now reſolved into Parochial Churches, within the Dioceſes of the Reſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive Cities, were United under the Juriſdiction of the Reſpective Biſhop of each City; So that <hi>the Vniting of many particular Churches, Miniſters &amp; People
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:35221:12"/>into one Dioceſan Church, under the juriſdiction of a Prelate,</hi> is <hi>true Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity</hi> as uſed in Primitive times, by which it appears, that this Gent. Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, viz.<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.16.</note> 
               <hi>that there may be true Church <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity without Epiſcopacy,</hi> is a mere Innovation, there being no ſuch cuſtom in the Churches of God as the Apoſtle ſpeaks.</p>
            <p>As for their Officers they have the Sanction of our Laws to Authorize them; an Authority far greater than can be ſhewed for Lay Elders; Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers ſubſerviant to the Miniſter of every Congregation, and thô generally ignorant, and many of them cannot write their Names, yet are made judges of their fellow Chriſtians ſufficiency in faith; a novelty created by <hi>Calvin,</hi> and how reaſonable let the impartial judge. He ſays, <hi>ſo a man may plead to the juriſdiction of a Dioceſſan Prelate, may ſtep over Pariſh bounds,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>So did <hi>Korah</hi> and his Congregation againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Nam.</hi> 16.2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 10.</note> their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie being the very ſame with yours againſt the Church; they were for leveling the Prieſt-hood, ſo are you; they were for ſetting up a new model'd Congregation, ſo are you; God ſhewed his diſpleaſure againſt their Pride and Diſobedience, by a moſt terrible deſtruction; and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoever things were written aforetimes, were written for our Learning.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the end of p. 17. and in 18. he lays to my charge, that I <hi>diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not betwixt the extraordinary power which was properly Apoſtolical, and that ordinary Paſtoral Power which was eminently comprehended in the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Authority and Government of the Church muſt have expired with the Apoſtles, had not this <hi>Power</hi> been conveyed by their Delegation to their Succeſſors, by virtue whereof <hi>the ordinary Paſtoral power,</hi> viz. <hi>Power</hi> to Preach the Goſpel, Adminiſter Sacraments, Abſolve Penitents, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> was and is confer'd upon the Presbyters: <hi>the extraordinary and Apoſtolic Power</hi> of Ordaining and Governing, of Binding and Looſing, being intirely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in the Biſhop, the Apoſtles Succeſſors; and this too, <hi>of the ordinary Paſteral power</hi> is (to uſe his own words) <hi>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inently comprehended in the Dioceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Biſhops,</hi> as it was in the Apoſtles. Other diſtinction than this, cannot be truly made as I ſuppoſe. Then he maliciouſly mentions <hi>the Arch-biſhop of</hi> Canter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ury; what Chriſtian temper or good manners he ſhews therein, let the Reader judge? For it is written, Thou ſhalt not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of thy People. <hi>The Nature and Extent of the Epiſcopal Office</hi> being fuily ſtated, anſwers what he ſaith in the bottom of his 18 p. He ſays, Dr. Hammond <hi>tells us that all the Elders we read of in the Scripture, were Biſhops, and that every particular Church had one of theſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gent. has this quality, he never mentions the place where the thing may be ſound in any Author he quotes, which is not fair. Dr.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:35221:12"/>
               <hi>Hammond</hi> ſays indeed; <q>That the Biſhops in every City were the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors of the Apoſtles.</q>
               <note place="margin">Diſſert. <hi>3</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> In his <hi>Anot. on Acts c.</hi> 11. <hi>b.</hi> and in his Tracts of the Power of the Keys; <hi>Aſian</hi> Biſhops called Angels; and Biſhop and Elder terms equivalent, (which were written in Vindication of his Diſſerta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, from the exceptions of the Aſſembly of Divines (as they were called) wherein he has, by Scripture, the Primitive Fathers and undeniable Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments evinced (to the ſilenceing of the Aſſemblers) that the word Biſhop in Scripture did always ſignifie a Prelate or a Dioceſan Biſhop; and that the word Elder had the ſame ſignification; ſo that if this Gent. will be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded by the Author he has cited, his pretentions to Parochial and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Biſhops are at an end.</p>
            <p>P. 19. he ſays, <hi>tis pritty to hear him ſay, theſe two</hi> (that is <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus</hi>) <hi>were ordained Biſhops by the Apoſtles; was there any Apoſtle concerned beſides</hi> Paul <hi>in it? Here lies the trick,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whether they <hi>were Ordained</hi> by St. <hi>Paul</hi> alone, or with others conjunct, it was all one, being I was only to prove, that their being <hi>Ordained</hi> Biſhops was by Apoſtolic power, which being done thô by St. <hi>Paul</hi> alone is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. Nothing but prejudice and ill nature could ſee any thing of a Trick in this.</p>
            <p>Then he puts the Queſtion; <hi>and how (pray) could</hi> Timothy <hi>and</hi> Titus <hi>ſucceed the Apoſtles in the See of</hi> Epheſus <hi>and</hi> Crete, <hi>whilſt the Apoſtles were living?</hi> And then he is pleaſed in his 20 p. to Droll and ſcoff at 'em, and then ſays, <hi>to be the Apoſtles Succeſſors, the Apoſtles yet alive, and in plenitude of Power is a very great Myſtery,</hi> (ſo is all the Goſpel) then he cloſes, mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf merry with the ignorance of a Vicar of <hi>Newport</hi> (who, by the way is ſaid to have been a Nonconformiſt) which in a matter ſo momen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, carries too much levity for a Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>I ſaid in my p. 3. this Apoſtolical Succeſſion was begun in <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> &amp;c. They could not have been ſaid to be Succeſſors of Apoſtolical power, if the Apoſtle moved by the Holy Ghoſt had not <hi>whilſt living,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd it on them; could the Apoſtle have <hi>Ordained</hi> them after he was dead? The Apoſtle by Ordaining them in his life time, ſecured the Succeſſion to them, and the Government too in the Apoſtles abſence, even whileſt he was living; ſo that it was not improperly ſaid, that this Apoſtolic power was begun in <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi> they being the firſt mentioned in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who were inveſted with Epiſcopal power of Juriſdiction, by Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Ordination; that this Succeſſion of Biſhops <hi>is</hi> (as he ſcoſſingly calls it) <hi>a very great Myſtery</hi> is very true, the Biſhops being by virtue of this Succeſſion, as truly the Repreſentatives of Chriſt Jeſus, as Ambaſſadors are of Kings.</p>
            <p>In p. 20. he ſays I affirmed that no Presbyters had power to Ordain,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:35221:13"/>He deſires me <hi>to try, how I will reconcile this with Dr.</hi> Hammond, who ſays <hi>theſe Presbyters were all Biſhops;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14.</note> 
               <hi>or with Scripture it ſelf, that ſays even</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy <hi>received the Gift, by the laying on the Hands of the Presbitery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have try'd, and find it eaſily <hi>reconciled with Dr.</hi> Hammond, for his Judgment is, that thoſe Presbyters who joyn'd in that Ordination were A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, which you may ſee in his Paraphraſe on the above-mentioned Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and he refers to Note on <hi>Acts chap.</hi> 11. <hi>f.</hi> for his reaſons.<note place="margin">Mere Preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mea pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain, firſt found in the Church of Rome.</note> The firſt clear Inſtance of mere Presbyters aſſuming the power to Ordain, is to be found in the Church of Rome, as the learned Primate <hi>Bramhal</hi> tells us, p. 164. and in p. 431. he ſaith, <q>We may juſtly aſcribe the <hi>reviveing</hi> of the Aerian Hereſy to the Diſpenſations of the Court of Rome, who Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſed Ordinary Prieſts to Ordain and Confirm, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>In p. 20. he further ſaith, <hi>for propagation of Apoſtolical Succeſſion,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I inform 'em, that</hi> Linus <hi>by Apoſtolical Conſecration Succeeded the Apoſtles in the See of</hi> Rome; <hi>here is a double blunder again,</hi> Linus <hi>ſucceeded whilſt the Apoſtles were alive. How elſe could he have Apoſtolical Conſecration,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>The beſt way to determin this, is to obſerve the Rule which in great Wiſdom our Law hath appointed for Jurors, to bring in their Verdict ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their beſt Evidence: The beſt Evidence in this Caſe, are the writings of the Fathers who lived in the next Age, among whom, <hi>Irenaeus</hi> is accounted the moſt exact Notary of the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of Biſhops to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolic Sees;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>C.</hi> 3.</note> he affirms, that <q>
                  <hi>Linus</hi> was made Biſhop by the Apoſtles, and that he Succeeded St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that next after him <hi>Cletus</hi> (by ſome called <hi>Anen Cletus</hi>) Succeeded in that See:</q> and with him<note n="‖" place="margin">Lib. <hi>1.</hi> adv. Her. Sect. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Epiphanius</hi> agrees; and with theſe diverſe others; now this is ſo far from being <hi>a blunder,</hi> that it is a clear Manifeſtation of the great care the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles had of providing for <hi>the Succeſſion</hi> in their life time, which no man can object againſt, much leſs <hi>profanely</hi> Ridicule (as my Adverſary does) who will conſider that otherwiſe the Succeſſion muſt have failed, and been extinct if neglected whil'ſt the Apoſtles lived.</p>
            <p>In the 21 p. at the bottom, he ſaith, That my affirming, that this line of Apoſtolic Succeſſion of Biſhops, hath continued in all Ages to this preſent time;<note place="margin">Succeſſion of Biſhops from the Apoſtles without interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to this Age.</note> 
               <hi>is</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>an aſſertion without the leaſt ſhaddow of proof; yea contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the acknowledgment of all Church Hiſtorians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If this Gent, had mentioned where any <hi>Church Hiſtorian</hi> of Credit, is of his Opinion, and ſhewed when any interruption happened, he had done ſomething for the ſupport of his opinion. But let him examine from this preſent age, to the days of <hi>Lucius</hi> King of the <hi>Northumbers,</hi> (who is credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſaid to be the firſt King that Embraced the Chriſtian Faith in this Iſle) and if he can aſſign one Breach of this Succeſſion, he out does his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:35221:13"/>but if not, he ſtands guilty of bringing a falſe Accuſation againſt all truly Catholic Churches. For not only the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> but all other Eſtabliſhed Catholic Churches do aſſert the Succeſſion of their Biſhops, to deſcend from the Apoſtles: And it is in every Dioceſs as ſacredly Recorded as the <hi>Succeſſion</hi> of <hi>Rings</hi> and <hi>Emperors</hi> to their Thrones.</p>
            <p>But in p. 22, he ſays, <hi>The very Papiſts themſelves, confeſs that there are inſuperable difficulties about the Succeſſion of Popes in the Roman See.</hi> My Adverſary would rebuke ſuch boldneſs in me; I never diſcourſed with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of that Church who did not zealouſly aſſirm the Succeſſion; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve they may challenge him to name any of them, or ſhew any Books of theirs, wherein he can find ſuch a <hi>Confesſion</hi> as he alledgeth. In the days of <hi>Valentinian,</hi> there was great ſtrife about the Claim of that <hi>See;</hi> yet none was put into poſſeſſion who had not Epiſcopal Conſecration, in which reſpect the Epiſcopal <hi>Succeſſion</hi> was preſerved; ſo that the <hi>inſupera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble difficulties,</hi> are but his bare Allegation.</p>
            <p>But pray how can there be a Prieſt without <hi>this Line of Apoſtolic Succeſſion?</hi> Can a man receive Prieſtly, <hi>i. e.</hi> Spiritual Power, by laying on of the hands of them who have not <hi>Power</hi> to confer it; it is St. <hi>Pauls</hi> queſtion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.14, 15. <hi>how ſhall they hear without a Preacher, and how ſhall they Preach except they be ſent,</hi> &amp;c. which is a ſtrong affirmation, that no man ought to preach without Divine Miſſion. The great Biſhop of our Souls was ſent of God, the Apoſtles received their Miſſion from him, and no man can ſay he is ſent, (that is) can truly be a Miniſter of the Goſpel, who hath not Apoſtolical Miſſion, and no man hath <hi>power</hi> to ſend, who hath not receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it by <hi>Succeſſion</hi> from the Apoſtles: and this <hi>Succeſſion</hi> muſt be by an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interrupted Line from the Apoſtles, or it ceaſes to be Divine; ſo that the abſolute neceſſity of an uninterrupted Line is a ſufficient reaſon to prove it. And now I may affirm, that great Catholic truth (it remaining firm and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken) ſet down in my former paper, p. 3. <hi>(viz.)</hi> who ever he be that is out of this Line of Apoſtolic Succeſſion, and Exerciſes any Miniſterial Office, without the Commiſſion of Epiſcopal Ordination, can be no more or other, then a Lay Impoſtor and a Schismatic, and that without <hi>expoſing Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity it ſelf</hi> (as he ſays p. 23. I do) or without <hi>leaving the Conſciences of all the men in the World, at an utter uncertainty; whether they have a true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry. or true Ordinances or no;</hi> for there is no other way wherein <hi>a true Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi> and conſequently <hi>true Ordinances</hi> can be found, and this is ſo far from <hi>Leaving mens Conſciences at an uncertainty,</hi> that it is the only foundation of certainty and aſſurance of <hi>a true Miniſtry,</hi> and conſequently <hi>true Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances,</hi> and from whence we receive real comfort in the Participation;
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:35221:14"/>for other Foundation, ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> can no man lay, than that is already lay'd, which is Jeſus Chriſt; (1 <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 3. verſ. 11.) Jeſus Chriſt hath founded his Church upon the Holy Apoſtles, and ſo as not to be demoliſhed, or expire with their lives, but to continue firm in their Succeſſors to the end of the World; to deny this is both to diſtruſt the power and providence of God, and to make void the promiſe of our Lord, made, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.20.</p>
            <p>But this my Adverſary does; for (ſays he in p. 24.) <hi>in how many Caſes may this Line be broken, and all the Apoſtolic power conveyed there, be ſpilt and loſt,</hi> &amp;c. Is not this mans Faith too weak in the power of God, and in the promiſe of his Son? Which is, <hi>that the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt her, Mat.</hi> 16.18. that is his Church; and ſhall the devices of men out do the Gates of Hell? ſhall the fancy of this man and his Brethren over-throw that againſt which, God hath promiſed the powers of Hell ſhall not prevail? And becauſe theſe men infatuated by Error, deſpiſe this Church, whoſe Foundation was laid by the bleſſed Jeſus, and hath the power of the Keys of the Kingdom of Heaven committed to her, muſt ſhe be made a Prey and a Sacrifice to the blind Ignorance, Pride and Luſts of theſe mens minds, to make way for the Whimſy and Invention of man; not known or heard of in the Church of Fourteen hundred years? Muſt the power of Preaching the Goſpel, Abſolving Penitents, Conſecrating the Holy Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> be loſt and made void by being tranſlated into prophane hands, to be Officiated by thoſe who are not ſent of God? All which, are the unavoidable conſequences of this man's Doctrine. For he ſays p. 24. <hi>Where this Line is broken all</hi> this Apoſtolic power is ſpilt and loſt.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Abbot of</hi> Hy was objected by a Popiſh Writer to prove our Church Schiſmatical, and it is now brought by this Diſſenter againſt the <hi>Apoſtolic Succeſſion,</hi> which in his p. 25. he names in the Margin. The moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Primate <hi>Bramball,</hi> in anſwer to the Papiſt, writes a juſt Vindication of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. In p. 131, and 135, of his works, you have an account at large, where he clears the <hi>Northumbrian</hi> Biſhops from <hi>Receiving Conſecration of the Abbot of</hi> Hy, and ſhews, that they had their Conſecration from the Biſhop of <hi>Derry,</hi> (then called <hi>Derry-magh</hi>) under whoſe Viſitation this <hi>Abbot</hi> lived: The Primate tells us, the Records were to be ſeen at <hi>Derry</hi> before the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebellion; and this ſtory you have much to the ſame purpoſe, in the Lord Biſhop of St. <hi>Aſaph's Hiſtorical ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt of Church Government,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Chap.</hi> 5. ſo that this Diſſenter has no more advantage with the Popiſh Writer againſt our Church, by caſting this Imputation out of this Story, to break the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> then the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt had to prove us Schiſmaticks; nor is any <hi>interciſion</hi> hereby proved which my Adverſary pretends.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:35221:14"/>
            <p>In the ſame p. 25. he deſires to know of me, or any who encourages me to write little Books, <hi>Whether this Line of Succeſſion may be continued in a Schiſmatical Church; and the Apoſtolical Power conveyed thereby?</hi> (ſays he) <hi>if by Schiſm men and Societies are cut off from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, then ſuch Schiſmatical Churches are no Churches,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>What occaſion I gave him for this queſtion, you may ſee in my 3d. Page; after I affirmed the Apoſtolical Succeſſion of Biſhops, and inferred from thence, that who ever Exerciſed any Miniſterial Office out of this <hi>Line of Succeſſion,</hi> and had not Epiſcopal Ordination,<note place="margin">No true Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of the line of Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</note> could be no other than a Lay Impoſtor and a Schiſmatic; then I inferred further, and conſequently all Societies of Chriſtians who with-draw themſelves from the Government of their Biſhops; who are the Apoſtles Succeſſors, and from Communicating with thoſe Presbyters lawfully ſet over them by Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal Ordination and Inſtitution: and frame themſelves into any other ſort of Government, are guilty of Schiſm; ſuch Societies are Schiſmatics, and cut themſelves off from the Catholic Church, but can in no ſort pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly be call'd Churches, and therefore I underſtand not his Logic in this, (viz.) <hi>If by Schiſm, Men and Societies are cut off from the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church, therefore Schiſmatical Churches are no Churches.</hi>
               <note n="‖" place="margin">The Donatiſts were ſuch</note> 
               <hi>Churches</hi> they are, thô <hi>Schiſmatical;</hi> whilſt they retain the Apoſtolical Succeſſion, they retain al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo the power and Authority of Ordination, Preaching the Goſpel, and Adminiſtring the Sacraments, and ſo retain the name of a Church.<note n="*" place="margin">Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters no right to the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion.</note> But what are our Diſſenters concerned herein? They diſclaim the <hi>Succeſſion,</hi> and deny any <hi>power</hi> or Virtue to be derived from it, and therefore have no Commiſſion to preach the Goſpel, or Adminiſter Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and conſequently no right to the name of a Church; but by the word <hi>Societies</hi> they would have Churches underſtood, that thereby their Unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies might paſs under that Title.</p>
            <p>I muſt here put one queſtion to theſe Diſſenters; many of the Clergy of the Romiſh Church have embraced Communion with the Reformed Churches; I deſire to know whether Re-ordination in this caſe was ever required? the anſwer muſt be in the Negative, their Ordination being derived from the Apoſtles Succeſſors; in vain then is this Gentleman's at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to Un-church the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as in his p. 25.) for <hi>that our Biſhops have derived their Conſecration from the Church of</hi> Rome, it being the Judgement of all Reformed Divines, that formal Schiſm cannot inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lidate the power of Regular and formal Ordination.</p>
            <p>In p. 26. he ſays <hi>I would Exclude all the Reformed Churches beyond Sea that have not thoſe Governors,</hi> &amp;c. by <hi>thoſe Governors,</hi> I ſuppoſe he means Dioceſan Biſhops.</p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:35221:15"/>
            <p>To this I anſwer; That many very Learned and Pious perſons among them, have declared their longing deſires for the Epiſcopacy, but living in Popiſh Dominions, cannot have any but thoſe of the Romiſh Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. Others there be, that approve of it, yet live in Republic Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and they will by no means admit of Epiſcopacy in that Regiment; invincible neceſſity is upon theſe, and therefore in Charity cannot be charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Schiſm, being in their deſires Catholic; but as for thoſe who with you, and your Brethren in <hi>England,</hi> deny its Authority, and obſtinately refuſe Subjection to it, they with you are notorious Schiſmatics, and can in no wiſe be excuſed.</p>
            <p>As for that fanciful ſuppoſition of <hi>a Company of Chriſtians caſt upon a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Iſland</hi> (which he talks of in p. 26.) <hi>or if all the Paſtors in a Country ſhould be put to death,</hi> &amp;c. He cannot bring one inſtance of either, and if it ſhould ſo happen, all the Lay-men and mere Presbyters in the World cannot make one Evangelical Prieſt; cannot impower them to Preach the Goſpel, not Conſecrate Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but what can be expected from Invincible neceſſity? They have a God to pray to, whoſe mercies are infinite, <hi>who will fulfil the deſires of them that fear him, and will hear their cry,</hi> Pſal. 114. v. 19.</p>
            <p>In his 27 p. he ſaith, <hi>But if we aſſent to the Whimſie of a conſtant Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as if power were conveyed like water in a Conduit, after a Phiſical manner, by contact paſſing through the Fingers ends of the Prelate, into the noddle of the perſon Ordain'd,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Whimſie</hi> I take it, ſignifies ſome Phantaſtic Device, or the Creature of an unſtable, or unſettled brain; which being applyed or imputed to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates, who bear the Authority of Chriſt, deriving it Originally from him, can be no leſs (I think) than Blaſphemy, for our bleſſed Savior ſaith to his Apoſtles, and in them to their Succeſſors; <hi>He that deſpiſeth you, deſpiſeth me, and he that deſpiſeth me, deſpiſeth him that ſent me;</hi> Luke 18. v. 16. no man that has not arrived to the highth of wickedneſs, and given him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf over to a reprobate mind, would thus revile the Ambaſſadors of God; he can be no better than a <hi>filthy Dreamer,</hi> who thus <hi>deſpiſeth Dominion, and ſpeaks evil of Dignities.</hi> Jude, v. 8. How wantonly does this man ſport himſelf in holy things? and by vilifieing and contemning the Evangelical holy Prieſt-hood make void, and a kicſhaw (as much as in him lyeth) of our holy Religion, expoſing and proſtituting it to the contempt and ſcorn of Infidels and Atheiſts.</p>
            <p>What he mentions in p. 28. viz. <hi>The Leud Extravagant Careſſes that have happened between the ambitious Princes, and aſtiring Church-men</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns us not, for he cannot name any ſuch <hi>aſpiring Church-men that have
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:35221:15"/>been in</hi> England ſince the Reformation, and thô he could, the order be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Divine Inſtitution cannot be diſſolved for any mans miſcarriage; if by this he means any thing of the Church of Rome, we abjure her Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction over us. Dr. <hi>Sancroft</hi> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> with ſix other Biſhops, in their Addreſs to K. <hi>James,</hi> declared againſt the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurping of any abſolute Empire, over the Civil and Religious Rights of men,</hi> and this was done ſo publickly, that it is more than probable, the fame of it is gone thrô the World, ſo that this Inſinuation of his, is a mere malicious calumny.</p>
            <p>In my p. 4. I proved that to love as Chriſtians in Scripture ſence, is to love as members of Chriſt, and that this obliges Chriſtians to preſerve the Body (<hi>i. e.</hi> the Church) from Rents and Schiſms, which (ſays he) <hi>we ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver deny.</hi> He implicitly confeſſeth that they ought to preſerve the Church from Rents and Schiſms, and yet ſhamefully denys it in practice every day. I have ſo fully ſpoken of this before that I need ſay no more in this place.</p>
            <p>And here again are the Ceremonies objected, which thô I have proved to be no ſufficient ground for their Separation, yet for further ſatisfaction I will here Recommend the Reaſons given by the <hi>Convocation,</hi> why the Ceremonies were retained; They are affix'd before the Book of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Prayer, and are important enough, to ſatisfie the Conſcience of any ſober Conſciencious Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>In p. 29. he ſays, <hi>for our further Conviction we are told</hi> (the Communion of Saints is one External viſible Communion in the Chriſtian Church) <hi>which is ſo far from explaining the thing, that it makes it much darker;</hi> what I ſaid above, had reference to the Chriſtian Church when it was firſt called Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic. And was not the Communion of the Church then <hi>One?</hi> and ought it not to be ſo ſtill? and was not the Union <hi>External</hi> and <hi>Viſible?</hi> but I did a little after explain by ſhewing wherein this Communion doth more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly conſiſt: In my p. 5. <hi>(viz.)</hi> in the ſame Articles of Faith;<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints in Faith.</note> I nam'd the Apoſtles, <hi>Nicene</hi> and <hi>Atharaſian</hi> Creeds, which have been received and uſed in the Catholic Church, from the times they were firſt publiſhed, and appoint'd by the Authority of the Church; the Creeds are Compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ums and brief Comprehenſions of the Objects of our Chriſtian Faith, and do contain all things neceſſary to be believ'd; every Article being a prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of the Chriſtian Religion, which every Chriſtian is bound to profeſs, and is the Teſt to diſtinguiſh between Heretics and ſound Chriſtians; and now this profeſſion and agreement of Chriſtians in theſe Articles of Faith, may be truly called the Communion of Saints in point of Faith. But my Adverſary is not very fond of theſe Creeds; <hi>and why not in Scripture</hi> (ſays he) Why! every one who truly believes the Scripture, believes the Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:35221:16"/>of Faith, and every one who believe the Articles believe the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. He ſays, <hi>They are but Human compoſition.</hi> They were <hi>Compoſed</hi> by thoſe to whom the Care and Authority of the Church was committed, and every Article for the benefit of all, even the meaneſt Chriſtians, being form<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and Collected out of Sacred Scripture, are of Divine Authority.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>I ſhut out the Greek and other Eaſtern Churches.</hi> This is but his own Conception, for they agree with us in all Articles of Faith; they do not indeed expreſs the Article of the Holy Ghoſt in the very ſame words, but they acknowledge that the Holy Ghoſt proceedeth from the Father by the Son, which differs not in ſenſe, and they Worſhip the Trinity in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and Unity in Trinity, ſo that in Articles of Faith we and they hold Communion. Well! I perceive thô my Adverſary reliſhes not, and ſpeaks with but indifferent Reſpect of the Creeds, yet he ſays, however <hi>he is ſo far in Communion with us,</hi> ſo in this, he will be no Schiſmatic; or rather no Heretic.<note place="margin">The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Another particular (which I mentioned) requir'd in this Communion, is partaking all at the ſame Table; (which thô it be not <hi>individually</hi> yet Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually it is <hi>the ſame;</hi> and being every where called the Lords Table, could be no otherwiſe meant; but that this Gent. will be very witty, and take exceptions at every thing. The Apoſtle calls it the Lords Table. The Cup of Bleſſing which we bleſs,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cer.</hi> 10.21. <hi>v.</hi> 16. <hi>v.</hi> 17.</note> is it not the Communion of the Body of Chriſt? We being many, are one Bread and one Body, for we are all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of that one Bread. All true Chriſtians partaking at the Lords Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble are one Body in the Apoſtles Senſe; the bread not only ſignifieing the Body of Chriſt, but the Unity of the partakers alſo; and this is the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints at the Lords Table. Here, ſays he, <hi>we are with him ſtill.</hi> I wonder at his confidence; he would ſay ſure, <hi>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re we</hi> ought to be with them, for they are not with us. By comparing our Church with the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Churches, I have proved her to be a Church truly Catholic; her Juriſdiction as truly Apoſtolical as they were; from whence it follows (as I have ſaid) that her Orders are to be equally obey'd; her Unity and Peace as ſtrictly maintained, and what ſoever was Schiſm in any of them muſt be ſo in her.</p>
            <p>To refuſe Communicating with any of them at the Lords Table, and to have ſet up another Table in oppoſition to any of them, muſt in this Gentlemans judgment have been criminous Schiſm; then of neceſſity it holds true againſt our Diſſenters; they refuſe Communion with that Church which moſt certainly holds true Communion with the Univerſal Catholic Church, and conſequently with the Son of God, who is the Head thereof, and the Principle and proper Object of all Chriſtian Communion: Our
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:35221:16"/>Diſſenters have ſet up a ſeparate Table in oppoſition thereto, rob'd her of her Members, and broke her Unity; all this being notoriouſly the breach of Chriſtian Charity, is in this Gent. and Mr. <hi>Hery's</hi> Senſe too, Schiſm; which Mr. <hi>Hery</hi> calls an <hi>Arch-Rebel,</hi> (but not ſo properly) as an Infamous Rebellion <hi>in Chriſts Kingdom;</hi> and thus they are Schiſmatics in Separating from the Communion of Saints at the Lords Table. What he talks here, of <hi>deriving our Succeſſion from the Church of</hi> Rome, is already anſwered.</p>
            <p>A third particular required in this Communion, I affirmed to be,<note place="margin">Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints in the ſame Prayers.</note> the joyning all in the ſame holy Prayers and Supplications, Interceſſions and giving of thanks, according to St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s expreſs Command.</p>
            <p>To this he ſays, <hi>I cannot mean, that in thoſe Dutys we muſt neceſſaryly uſe the very ſame words,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for then I exclude all the World but them of my own perſwaſion, and a great many of them too.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I exhort therefore</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>that firſt of all, Supplications, Prayers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> Tim. <hi>2.</hi> v <hi>1.2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Interceſſions, and giving of Thanks be made for all min; for Kings and all that are in Authority,</hi> &amp;c. Here is a ſufficient ground from Holy Scripture, for Liturgies, or Forms of Prayers in the public Worſhip and Service of God; and St. <hi>Paul</hi> gives his reaſon for it in his Ep. to the <hi>Romans; that we might with one mind and one mouth, Glorifie God, the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. <hi>15.</hi> v. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> According to this command, Forms of Prayers or Liturgies were Compoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed early in the Catholic Churches, and have been uſed ever ſince, that there might be an Unity in their Supplications and Prayers, and in their Thankſgivings and Praiſes, that nothing ſhould be omitted, nor any thing more in our Petitions expreſs'd, but what our holy Religion requires, &amp; that there ſhould be no rudeneſs, or undecency in words (in which reſpects, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and Extempore prayers are very liable to be faulty) and in theſe, they were all obliged to joyn where ever they came together for the public Worſhip and Service of God: Herein they had Communion with God the Father, and with his Son Jeſus Chriſt, who was in the midſt of them,<note place="margin">Mat. <hi>28.</hi> v. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> and in whoſe name they were preſented, and with one another; Uniting all in the ſame Prayers; here is the Communion of Saints in holy Prayers. It is true, that the Reſpective Provincial or Dioceſan Churches had not e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one their ſet Forms of Prayers or Liturgies <hi>in the very ſame words;</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Biſhop having power to Compoſe a Form for that Church of which he was Over-ſeer: Yet they were the ſame for ſubſtance, ſo that every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian was obliged to Communicate not only with the Biſhop, or his Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters under whoſe Juriſdiction he lived, but all Catholics coming to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote Churches did, as bound by the Rules of Catholic Unity, Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicate with their Fellow-Chriſtians to what Church ſoever they came.</p>
            <p>That in this the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as in the former particulars) holds
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:35221:17"/>Communion with the Primitive Catholic Church will appear,<note place="margin">Pream Quinto &amp; Sexto Ed. 6 ti. cap. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi.</note> if we conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the CONVOCATION in the Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, by whom our Liturgie was Reform'd; with one conſent agreed upon one Set Form of Prayer, Adminiſtration of Sacraments <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to be uſed in the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> tongue in every Dioces thrô out the Realm; In the Reforming and Compoſure wherof, they had before their eyes, the Word of God and the <hi>Primitive Church</hi> for their imitation: the Glory of God, the Comfort and Edification of the People for their End: and all their Supplications and Prayers therein, are directed to God Almighty, preſented in the name of the bleſſed Jeſus; and all we ſupplicate for in them, is for no other, than what is allow'd of, and required in our holy Religion, and is a reaſonable Service.</p>
            <p>To this I will add two things more, <hi>viz.</hi> Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Letter to the then Protector of <hi>England,</hi> which is to this purpoſe. <hi>For ſo much as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns the Prayers and Eccleſiaſtical Rites, I much approve that they be deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined, ſo that it may not be Lawful for the Miniſters in their Adminiſtrations to vary from it;</hi> and he gives his Reaſons. <hi>That it may be a help to the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of ſome; That it may be a Teſtimony of the Churches Conſent, and that it may ſtop the deſultorious levity of thoſe who are for new things,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other is what their Learned Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Diſp. of Liturgy Prop. <hi>10</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant diſuſe of Forms, is apt to breed a giddineſs in Religion, and may make men Hypocrites, who ſhall delude themſelves with conceits, that they delight in God, when it is but in theſe Novelties and Verie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Expreſſion that they are delighted, and therefore he adviſeth Forms to fix Chriſtians, and make them ſound.</q> Thus theſe two great Guides of theirs.</p>
            <p>It being clear that there is a Communion of Saints in Prayers as in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Offices of Divine Worſhip; the refuſing to Commnuicate there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, is a Breach of Unity, and of the Communion of Saints. Nor can I ſtand charged (as my Adverſary affirms) with <hi>Excluding all thoſe from the Communion of Saints who uſe</hi> not the Liturgy of our Church; every National Catholick Church having equal Authority to enjoyn its own Liturgy, in which every Member therein is bound to Communicate by the very nature of Unity required in the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>John</hi> declares,<note place="margin">Revel. <hi>5.9.</hi> &amp;c.</note> that <hi>the Four and Twenty Elders</hi> in his viſion <hi>ſung a new Son<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and ſets down the Form of words wherein the <hi>Angels, the Beaſts, and the Elders,</hi> all <hi>with a load Voice glorified the Lamb,</hi> &amp;c. Now what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:35221:17"/>ever elſe this may ſignifie, it certainly Repreſents the Uniformity of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service above; and it is to be conſidered, that the Church on Earth is the Type of that glorious part of the Catholic Church Triumphant in Heaven; and thô the perfection of that Unity which is above, cannot be attained unto in this imperfect State which is below, yet that which is above is propoſed for our imitation, and ſheweth the great delight the <hi>Glorious Trinity</hi> the <hi>One God</hi> hath in the <hi>Vnity,</hi> of his Service. The nearer we on Earth Reſemble that Unity which is above, the more perfect we are. The <hi>Church of England,</hi> in Immitation of the Church above, enjoyns Unity in Her Prayers, Interceſſions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in all the Worſhip and Service of God; but in contradiction to this, our Diſſenters can by no means endure it.</p>
            <p>A Fourth particular (mentioned by me) required in the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, is;<note place="margin">Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints in ſubjection to Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors.</note> To be Subject and Odedient to our Spiritual Rulers, and Governors (who have derived their Authority from the Apoſtles by a due Succeſſion) in all things pertaining to Godly Life, Decen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and Order.</p>
            <p>To this he ſays in p. 31. and 32. <hi>We are very deſirous to give due Honour and Obedience to our Spiritual Governors, who derive their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority from Chriſt, which is more proper than to ſpeak of deriving it from the Apoſtles, for Chriſt is the only Fountain of Authority and the Stream; are derived rather from the Fountain than the Ciſtern; it is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, the mans expreſſion is ſunk from an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ninterrupted Succeſſion to a due Succeſſion: To obſerve the Apoſtolical precepts in Government and Worſhip may make it up a due Succeſſion, but there is more in an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ninterrupted one than ſo; now before he can ſay we want this Qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation for Communion, he muſt prove that Dioceſan Biſhops are made our Spiritual Rulers by a Divine Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For any man living to affirm that he has Received Authority to be a Miniſter of the Goſpel <hi>from Chriſt Jeſus</hi> immediately, is contrary to the current of the Goſpel and the voice of all Antiquity ſince the Apoſtles: Who but the Apoſtles can this be attributed unto? St. <hi>Paul,</hi> thô after the miraculous deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt upon the other Apoſtles, had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>a Commiſſion from Chriſt Jeſus</hi> immediately, yet it was confer'd in an extraordinary manner, by a voice from Heaven that it might appear to be no cheat, (<hi>Acts</hi> 13.3.) and he entred not upon his Office without the Impoſition of the hands of the Church. No ſpiritual Power is received <hi>from Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> by any man immediately; it is conferred no other way,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:35221:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>but from Chriſt to his Apoſtles, and by a Succeſſion from them to our days, the Original and <hi>Foundation thereof being Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> If any man will pretend to an immediate Authority, and prove it not by ſome Miracle or Revelation, he can paſs for no other than a mere Enthuſiaſt and an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtor. This Doctrin of his, is the falſe bottom upon which many Hereſies, ſtrange and pernicious Opinions have been built, and is the Parent of our Schiſms, and Separations; if a man by this Suggeſtion can but gull the weak people, into a belief of ſuch a Commiſſion to be immediately from Chriſt, How do they follow and admire him? With-draw their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence from their lawful Governors and Paſtors, break the bonds of Charity, and all the Rules of Peace and Order? and all this only to be the Diſciples of ſuch a man. All <hi>the Honor and Obedience</hi> theſe men give, is not to <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Governors</hi> who are ſo by the Inſtitution of our Lord. Jeſus, to whom alone the promiſe of the Aſſiſtance and Operation of the bleſſed Spirit is given, to Guide and Govern the Flock of Chriſt; but to them who enter not by the door, but climb up ſome other way, <hi>i. e.</hi> thoſe, who are ſet up by their own Authority. That in many particulars theſe Diſſenters differ from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> wherein ſhe agrees with the Primitive Churches, doth by this time fully appear.</p>
            <p>My uſing the words, <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Succeſſion</hi> here, doth not (as he pretends) <hi>ſink</hi> the ſenſe of an Uninterrupted Succeſſion; for that cannot be called a <hi>due Succeſſion,</hi> which is not an Uninterrupted Succeſſion. So this is but a mere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ingle.</p>
            <p>I have before ſufficiently proved the Government of the Church by Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Epiſcopacy, to be the Inſtitution of our Bleſſed Saviour, and that our Dioceſan Biſhops in the Church of <hi>England</hi> are inveſted with this Divine Authority by an uninterrupted Succeſſion, and ſo are made our <hi>Spiritua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rulers</hi> by the ſame <hi>Divine Authority.</hi> Now theſe Diſſenters having this Divine Authority among 'em; it follows by my Adverſary's acknow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ledgment, that the Diſſenters in <hi>England want this Qualiſication for Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion,</hi> by which <hi>Communion</hi> muſt be underſtood <hi>the Communion</hi> of Saints.</p>
            <p>In the ſame p. he ſays, <hi>A ſingle perſon taking upon him to Govern ſome Thouſands of Congregations, by ſuch Rulers and Officers as our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Prela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy uſes, and this by the Nomination of the Civil Magiſtrate without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the people, or the Miniſters within the Dioceſs, is a Creature we find not in Scripture, nor in Primitive times, and therefore can be no Spiritual Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors of ours by Divine Right,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>That the Juriſdiction of <hi>Engliſh</hi> Prelates is of <hi>Divine Right</hi> being prov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, this <hi>Creature</hi> (as he ſcoffingly calls it) which he ſays, they <hi>can neither find in Scripture, nor in Primitive times,</hi> is evidently found in both, and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:35221:18"/>no other <hi>Creature,</hi> that is no other Government of the Church can be <hi>found</hi> in either; ſo that his objections againſt Congregations being nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous in a particular Dioceſs comes to nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Their Rulers and Officers</hi> are mentioned before. But it is worth Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to ſee, how the Regular Acceſſion of a Biſhop to his Dioceſs, is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liciouſly called by him, <hi>a ſingle Perſon taking it upon himſelf,</hi> as if it were mere Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>But that which he ſeems to be much Scandalized at, <hi>is their Nomination by the Civil Majeſtrate without the conſent of the people, or the Miniſters of the Dioceſe.</hi> If it would not ſwell my papers too much, I could give him ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry many Inſtances to prove that for many Ages the <hi>Nomination</hi> of Biſhops hath been in the Right of Chriſtian Emperors and Chriſtian Kings; and that it hath been ſo, very Anciently in <hi>England,</hi> and ther's great reaſon it ſhould be ſo, for they were the Founders of Biſhopricks; who elſe then can of Right lay claim to the Patronage of preſenting to them? what confuſion would be the reſult? how endleſs the Feuds and Animoſitys in every Dioces, were their Elections Tumultuary and Popular? By the Presbyters of the Dioces they are Elected, the Dean and Chapter in every Dioces being their Repreſentatives, and this is to prevent Animoſities and Diviſions among the Clergie, in the Election of Biſhops; and the Clergie or any other Perſon as well without, as within the Dioces have liberty to put in any Allegation they have againſt him, and the Crime, if proved Judicially, invalidates the Election and all proceedings therein. So that all their Quarrel in this, is only againſt the Ancient Right of the Crown, and the wiſdom of the Clergie in preventing ſtrife and contention.</p>
            <p>That Dioceſan Biſhops are our <hi>Spiritual Rulers by Divine Authority</hi> being proved, anſwers all he ſays in his 32 and ends in his 33 <hi>P.</hi> His words are theſe, <q>When this man or any one for him, has made it appear that the Authority of a Dioceſan Prelat, Dean, Lay Chancellor <hi>&amp;c.</hi> over all in the Dioceſs is as Sacred as that of <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> we will not dare to diſpute it for ſeare of <hi>Corah's</hi> doom &amp;c. I hope he will not take it amiſs if we be not frighted out of our wits by ſuch miſapply'd paſſages <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Dean, Lay Chancellor <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are Prudential Officers and have not a Divine but a Legal, thô humane Authority; But the <hi>Authority of a Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan Prelate,</hi> conferr'd by, and derived from the Son of God muſt be <hi>as Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred as that of Moſes and Aaron,</hi> for the Apoſtle St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his Epiſt. to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> puts a far higher value and eſteem upon the Evangelical than the Aaronical Prieſthood; then certainly, to ſet up Congregations in defiance and combination againſt Evangelical Prieſihood, <hi>viz. Dioceſan Prelacy,</hi> is a Crime of as deep a Dy as that of Corah and his Congregation. Now thô
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:35221:19"/>I have more Charity than to have theſe men <hi>frighted out of their wits,</hi> yet I heartily wiſh, that they may be <hi>frighted</hi> into a ſence of their guilt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a fear of diſputing, the Crime being of the ſame Complexion with that of <hi>Corah;</hi> for althô God doth not now uſually avenge himſelf, againſt ſuch proud and obſtinate Offenders as he did to <hi>Corah</hi> by the imediate execution of his Judgments, yet he hath reſerved a Day, wherein his wrath againſt all deſpiſers of his Authority and all other unrighteouſneſſes of obſtinate and impenitent Sinners, will be revealed.</p>
            <p>He ſays <hi>Such miſapply'd paſages</hi> (<hi>viz.</hi> as that of Corah) <hi>they have often heard urged to back the Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rin of Non-reſiſtance and all thoſe Principles of Slavery ſome men have bee: endeavering to inſtil into our minds</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Be the conſequences what ever they may happen to be, <hi>the Doctrine of Non-reſiſtance</hi> was the Doctrin of the Holy Apoſtles; Theſe are the words of St. <hi>Paul, Let every Soul be Subject to the Higher Powers, for there is no Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer but of God: the Powers that be are Ordained of God. Whoſoever therfore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinance of God: and they that reſiſt receive to themſelvs Damnation.</hi> Rom 13.12. Theſe Precepts of the Apoſtle are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue eternally and are unalterable &amp; irreverſible by any human Authority whatſoever; To the obſervation wherof and obedience wherunto, all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are infallibly oblig'd. Now thô this <hi>Gent.</hi> may be above my advice, yet it will be his wiſdom not to preach any Doctrin contrary to this Divine Precept; not only becauſe it is contradicted by the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Government will puniſh it as Seditious</p>
            <p>He ſays in <hi>Pa.</hi> 33. <hi>In what Bounds he will ſix the Primitive Church we know not; certain it is a Century or Two made a conſiderable change in the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Goverment and Worſhip</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Let him and all his Fellow-Diſſenters lay their heads together, and if they will be ſo kind to themſelves, as to ſearch the Hiſtories of the Church, and the writings of the Fathers concerning the <hi>Goverment and Worſhip</hi> in the Church, and ſhew if they can, any <hi>change in the Goverment and worſhip</hi> in the three firſt Ceuturies, which until they perform my aſſertion ſtands firm. As for the <hi>change of Government</hi> which he ſo confidently affirms bare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon his own Authority and Fancy, is notoriouſly falſe, for what the <hi>Government</hi> was then, it has continued to be in all Catholic Churches to this day, ſo as that therin, there hath been no change at all.</p>
            <p>But ſays he in <hi>Pa.</hi> 34. <hi>If we muſt take our meaſures by theſe Churches that are truly Primitive, we fear not to put our ſelves to the Tryal</hi> &amp;c. Well! thô we have no Security that upon this Tryal they will ſtand to the Verdict, yet let it be Tryed.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:35221:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>That our Congregations have this Agreement in Faith none will deny.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Diſſenters agree not with the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church.</note> It is not the <hi>Agreement</hi> they have in their <hi>Congregations</hi> with one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother that can make them Catholics, but Agreement with the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Catholic Church,</p>
            <p>In the truly Primitive Church, all true Chriſtians did make a formal Profeſſion of Faith, by diſtinctly repeating the Creeds with an audible voice, as we do in our Churches at this day, which practice ſeems to be intimat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Injuction to <hi>Timothy; Hold faſt the Form of ſound Words which thou haſt heard of me,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 13.</note> What ever the Faith of theſe Separate Congregations may be, is unknown to us; the formal profeſſion of Faith which was conſtantly uſed by the Primitive Chriſtians, as the badge of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, being in the Congregations of our Diſſenters laid aſide. Now that they in this reſpect agree with the truly Primitive Church muſt <hi>be denied.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>I have not proved that they differ from the Catholic Church in the Eſſentials or integral parts of Gods Worſhip, or in any conſiderable Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. In the truly Primitive Churches they held ſtrict Communion with their Biſhops, who were the Apoſtles Succeſſors, and the Presbyters ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them by Epiſcopal Ordination and Inſtitution, not only <hi>in Eſſential,</hi> but in all Circumſtances in the Rites and Ceremonies of the Church alſo; as in the having all things Common, to this they yielded Conformity: The Love Feaſts, and the Holy-kiſs, mere Ceremonies, no Eſſentials of Worſhip, yet enjoyned by the Apoſtles as ſignificative of the ardent Love and Chriſtian Charity, which Chriſtians had for one another, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for ſome time after the Apoſtles days, till thrô Corruption grown to be Scandal, and then, thô Inſtituted by the Apoſtles, were aboliſhed by the Authority of the Church.</p>
            <p>Now our Diſſenters denying all Communion with our Biſhops who are the Apoſtles Succeſſors, and the Presbyters ſet over us by Epiſcopal Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation and Inſtitution; this, together with their Uſurping the Prieſtly Office without Epiſcopal Ordination, ſufficiently demonſtrates that our Diſſenters <hi>differ from the Primitive Catholie Church, in Eſſential, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Circumſtances,</hi> without any further trial.</p>
            <p>In p. 34. he further ſaith, <hi>And that this Divine Worſhip and Service is Viſible and External, this Gent. is but too ſenſible, and tis a very great Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore to ſuch as he, that it is ſo much more viſible than formerly it hath been.</hi> That it is viſible is true, but that it is Separate and out of the viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholic Church is as true.</p>
            <p>He is pleaſed to call it <hi>Divine Worſhip and Service</hi> which it cannot be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:35221:22"/>I ſuppoſe but only in reſpect of the Object; when they have a lawful Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Authority, that is Epiſcopal Ordination and Inſtitution without which there can be no true Miniſtry (which I have prov'd) and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly no true Ordinances, it may be called <hi>Divine Worſhip and Service,</hi> but till then, let they who are beſt able to judge, ſay what kind of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and Service it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lenatius</hi> will reſolve him in his Ep to the <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rn.</hi>
               <note place="margin">He ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note>
            </p>
            <p>That its <hi>being more vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ble than formerly is a great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ye <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>re to ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I am</hi> is a miſtake. I have known it <hi>more viſible</hi> than now it is; when all the Churches in the Kingdom were Uſurped into the poſſeſſion of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians, Independents, Anabaptiſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (thoſe were evil days) to ſee the Noble debaſed, the baſe and the vile made Rulers over us, Religion the pretence of Rebellion; the Church buried in Diſgrace and Calumny, call'd the <hi>Scariet Whore,</hi> &amp;c. He was admired for the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> man, the greateſt Saint, who was moſt improved in the Art of Rev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing and <hi>Speaking evil of Dignities;</hi> the quitting Communion with a truly Catno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c Church; the taking of a Rebellious Covenant (ſee his p. 54.) or human Compoſure, with ſignificant Ceremonies; ſubmitting to Lay Elders a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty not formerly known in the Chriſtian Church; theſe, with many other Miſeries and Calamities endured in thoſe days, <hi>were great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> to me and ſuch as I am.</hi> But we have learned by the Doctrin which our Church Teacheth, Acquieſcence and Submiſſion to the Legiſlative Power; (a Leſſon which out Diſſenters could never yet put in practice) T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y have granted you a Toleration, and we are ſo far from envying it, that we Acquieſs and ſubmit, ſo as to me and ſuch as I am, it is no otherwiſe an <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> than in Chriſtian Charity to pity your miſtakes, and heartily wiſh, that in your practice you would be more conformable to the Goſpel of Peace, and that there be Peace in the end.</p>
            <p>In his laſt Parag. p. 34. he ſays my aſſerting the Succeſſion of Biſhops from the Apoſiles, &amp;c. <hi>is inconſiſtent with other parts of my lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>k,</hi> and (ſav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) he <hi>ſuppoſeth he hath ſufficiently made it man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> and in p. 35. he calls my affirmations in my former paper, <hi>Crude and Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> apprehenſion;</hi> he is ſo kind, as to plead <hi>my capacity to excuſe me for my Blunders,</hi> (as he calls 'em) but ſays <hi>it will by no means leſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the fault: my O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ious and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, in meddleing with things I ſo little underſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is but Condemning me by the lump, and being paſt his skill to ſhew ſuch <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſiſtency in my Book,</hi> it is falſe, and thoſe which he calls my <hi>Blunders,</hi> I have proved to be undeniable Truths; all the ill is, that what ever theſe men ſpeak or write, be it ever ſo repreachful or falſe, their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples believe and ſwallow it for truth: But with Impartial men, Railing will never paſs for Conviction, nor moroſe &amp; uncharitable Cenſures for true
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:35221:22"/>Judgment; nor can the Imperious Language he ſo liberally beſtows upon me, add one mite to their Cauſe, nor one mite leſſen that eſteem (how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſerved ſoever) I have among many good men; but I have learned to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give him, ſhould be offend Seventy times ſeven.</p>
            <p>Having made the Epiſcopacy Eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear to be an exact paralel with the Catholic Churches in the Primitive times, what I mentioned of the Fathers, (in my p. 7.) holds good againſt my Adverſary by his own Allowance, as you may ſee in his p. 35. at the bottom, his words are theſe. <hi>We are no way concerned i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Citation of the Fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ht in againſt us, till he has proved that Epiſcopacy then, was the ſame thing it is m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, and that the Terms of Communion we ſcruple were ever impeſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them.</hi> The former part, that the Epiſcopacy in our Church is the ſame as it was then, is proved.</p>
            <p>That the having all things common, the Love-feaſts and the Holy-kiſs, <hi>mere Ceremonies; no Eſſentials in Religion,</hi> yet were Terms of Communion in the Apoſtles time, being very plain: That the Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies appointed by our Church, tho they are not ſpecifically the <hi>ſame</hi> (which this man ſeems to inſiſt upon) yet being in Nature the <hi>ſame</hi> with thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove mentioned. and being enjoyn'd by the ſame power and Authority derivatively, which the Apoſtles had; this Gent. or any other ought no more <hi>to ſcruple the Terms of Communion impoſed by our Church,</hi> than the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Chriſtians did <hi>ſcruple the Terms of Commanion impoſed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>In the bottom of his 35 p. he ſays, Ignatius <hi>charges the Biſhop to take Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nizance of every Member of his Church, not excepting the very Servants, and that it was the Cuſtom then, in every Congregation to receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment every Lords day, and that they never received it but from the Hand of the Biſhop.</hi> Hence he concludes <hi>that ſuch Biſhops muſt be the Paſtors of ſingle Congrezations; and adds, that this Argument has been copiouſly mannaged by</hi> Blundel, Baxter, Owen, Clarkſon, <hi>and others.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gent. as in all other Quotations, leaves me to find this; I have met with the paſſage in St. <hi>Ignatius's</hi> Ep. to <hi>Polycarp</hi> Biſhop of the <hi>Smyr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans;</hi> where he ſaith, <q>Converſe with all, man by man as God ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e thee;</q> he ſaith further, Let nothing be done without thy Sentence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A little farther he ſaith, <q>Let Congregations be gather'd more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, and take the names of all Perſons: Let neither Men nor Maid Servants be deſpiſed by thee.</q> And in the ſame Ep. he ſaith; <q>Be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of the Biſhop, that God may be mindful of you. I could give my Life for thoſe perſons who are Subject to the Biſhop, Presbyters, and Deacons.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:35221:21"/>
            <p>Let the Reader conſider all the parts together and then Judge, how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably <hi>Congregational Biſhops</hi> can be hence inferr'd?</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is evident that <hi>Polycarp</hi> was not Biſhop of one <hi>Single Congregation</hi> only; by theſe words, <hi>call the Congregations together</hi> &amp;c. in the Plural Number.</p>
            <p n="2">2. His Juriſdiction and Authority over the Congregations, is manifeſt in theſe words, <hi>Let nothing be done without thy Sentence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The Subjection <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Biſhop from theſe Congragations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd in this Exhortation to them; <hi>Be mindful of the Biſhop that God may be mindful of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The Diſtinction of the three Sacred Orders in the Church (about which theſe men have made ſuch a busſle in the world) are plainly ſet down and overthrows all their pretentions to Congregational Biſhops, for ſaith he, <hi>J could give my life for theſe perſons who are Subject to the Biſhop, Preſ y<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and Deacons.</hi> Here is a plurality of Congregations and a plurality of Presbyters and Deacons and but one Biſhop. From his not reading, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing the moſt material parts in this Ep. wherein lye the true Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of St. <hi>Ignatius,</hi> how Triumphantly does he conclude for <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Biſhops;</hi> whereas the whole is altogether againſt it. Then he glories in <hi>the copious management of this Argument, by</hi> Blundel, Baxter, Owen, Clarkſon, <hi>and others:</hi> Alaſs, all theſe have been judiciouſly Anſwered by <hi>Bramhal, Hammond, Morris, Stillingfleet, Dodwell,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>In his 36. p. ſaith he; <hi>It is obſervable in the paſſage cited out of</hi> Irenaeus, <hi>the Presbyters are ſaid to have their Succeſſion from the Apoſtles;</hi> and infers from thence, <hi>that the Presbyters are the Apoſtles Succeſſors as well as Biſhops, and muſt conſeq ently have the ſame power.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How frequently in the writings of the Fathers, and in Scripture, are Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops called Presbyters, as that word ſignifies Seniority or Dignity? and are not they ſometimes called Deacons too? but as it would be very ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd to infer from hence an Equality of Biſhops and Deacons, ſo would it be unreaſonable to conclude concerning Biſhop and Presbyter.</p>
            <p>That our Author is miſtaken in St. <hi>Irenaeus</hi>'s ſenſe of the word Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, appears by the words immediately ſubjoyned, which are theſe; <hi>Qui cum Epiſcopatus Succeſſione Chariſma veritatis certum, Secundum placitum Patris acceſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>L.</hi> 4. <hi>C.</hi> 43.</note> Who (that is the Presbyters above mentioned) with the Succeſſion of Epiſcopacy, have received the Infallible Gift of Truth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Will of the Father. It is plain that no other can be here ment, but thoſe of the higheſt Order in the Church; Biſhops.</p>
            <p>My Author p. 37. accuſeth me, that I deſigned not fair dealing with Mr. <hi>H-ry;</hi> it was a great omiſſion in me, I therefore take his (thô very
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:35221:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſharp) Rebuke very kindly. Mr. <hi>H-ry</hi> in his 19 p. Parag. 6. very Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxly ſaith: <hi>Separation from Communion with thoſe that we have joyned our ſelves to, without a Cauſe; give me leave to call it Separation for Separation ſake, without any regard had to any think amiſs in the Church we Separate from, or any thing better in that we joyn our ſelves to; is Schiſm.</hi> Then he proves the truth of this Propoſition, from his own deſcription of Schiſm; and then concludes, <hi>When we quite caſt off Communion with our Brethren out of Ambition, Animoſity to their perſons, affectation of Novelty and Singulari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and the like.</hi> Now our Author, leſt this truth ſo plainly ſet down by Mr. <hi>H-ry,</hi> ſhould carry too ſharp an edge upon 'em; in p. 37. brings in his Inſinuation (as he in vain ſuppoſeth) to guard them from the ſtroke they muſt naturally receive from the applying of it to them: For (ſays he) <hi>We all grant, that for perſons wilfully to with-draw themſelves from ſuch par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches as are framed according to Scripture Rules, and impoſe no new and needleſs Terms, is to act Schiſmatically, becauſe ſuch wilfull Separation can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be without the breach of Charity.</hi> The difficulties which my Author (which indeed are none at all) would put, lyes in <hi>Churches framed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture Rules,</hi> &amp;c. It is Schiſm in Mr. <hi>H-ry's</hi> Judgment <hi>to Separate from a Church without any regard had to any thing amiſs,</hi> Let it be Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined if in our Church there be any thing amiſs?</p>
            <p>Are not all the Arcicles of ſaving Faith truly taught?<note place="margin">No juſt cauſe of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> the Holy Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments duly Adminiſtred, the Moral precepts, and all the Rules of the Chriſtian Religion plainly and conſtantly recommended unto us, and preſt upon us for our Excerciſe in the whole Courſe of our lives, in the Sermons of our Clergy in all our Churches? are not all things pertaining to a God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life and Salvation by our Church fully exhibited to us, ſo as that no man can miſcarry but by his own fault? Here, then ſure can be nothing <hi>am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs.</hi> Can theſe men maintain and juſtifie then, the truth of their Doct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, and ſeparate themſelves from us without pronounceing themſelves Schiſmatics? either their Doctrin is not true, or theſe men are Schiſmatics in practice by their own ſhewing. All the falſe and ſhiftleſs pretence they have is, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not framed according to Scripture Rules, and impoſeth new and needleſs terms, and therefore Separation from ſuch a Church is no Schiſm.</p>
            <p>That our Church is truly Apoſtolical, and as truly framed as <hi>Jeruſalem, Antioch, Alexandria,</hi> and all other Primitive Churches according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rules; according to Chriſt Jeſus's own Inſtitution, is fully proved in theſe papers. So that, that Objection is clearly Anſwered, and is indeed vain and frivolous.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:35221:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Now let his other as vain and frivolous Objection be conſidered; <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Impoſing new and needleſs Terms,</hi> by which is, I ſuppoſe, meant Gere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies; I muſt here crave leave to mention what I have before; <hi>viz.</hi> the Love-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>caſt, the Holy. kiſs had no intrinſic vertue in them, were no Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tials of Religion (ſee his p. 2.) mere Ceremonies; and as this Gent. calls our Ceremonies, <hi>without any native worth, or ſtrength,</hi> yet were made Terms of Communion in the Apoſtles days, and continued for ſome time after. The Ceremonies in our Church are of the ſame Nature; only have ſo much <hi>worth and ſtrength,</hi> that they beat the pleaſant fruit of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency and Order; they are falſly called <hi>New,</hi> being Cuſtoms of great An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity in the Church, and being enjoyned by the ſame power derivative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly which the Apoſtles had, (by my Adverſatys good leave) ceaſe to be needleſs: It neceſſarily follows, that all perſons within the Juriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iction of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Church, have the ſame Obligation to ſubmit to her Terms of Communion, as the Chriſtians had to ſubmit to the Terms o. Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the Apoſtles: Seeing then, that there's nothing amiſs in our Church <hi>i. e.</hi> not any thing that can give any juſt occaſion to ſeparate from her Communion: Seeing too, that She is a Church framed according to Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Rules, and that her Terms of Communion are neither New nor Need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; the Concluſion neceſſarily follows, that whoever they be within her Juriſdiction, that Separate from her Communion, do Separate for Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſake, and have no other Motives thereunto, than thoſe in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the mind, mentioned by Mr. <hi>Hery, viz</hi> Ambition Animoſity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to cloſe this; Theſe men are <hi>Notorious Schiſmaticks</hi> from their own Principles, &amp; thereby give themſelves the Title of <hi>Arch-Rebels</hi> in Chriſts Kingdom.</p>
            <p>I will t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> this Queſtion upon the Diſſenters, and Examin what account they can give or their being <hi>a Church framed according to Scripture Rules,</hi> and whether all they impoſe as Terms of Communion be <hi>by expreſs Rules in Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Church cannot be framed according <hi>to Scripture Rules</hi> where the Prieſtly Office is exerci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed without the Divine Miſſion; my Author may as tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> affirm in reſpect of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>atural Generation, that be is an immediate Son of <hi>Adam,</hi> as what be in his 31 p. affirms of Ordination, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>their Spiritual Govern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rs i.e.</hi> their Paſtors <hi>derive their Authority from Chriſt,</hi> which by the words ſub<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyned, muſt be immediately from Chriſt, for he ſays, <hi>it is mere proper than to ſpeak of deriving it from the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c. No Commiſſion was ever known to come immediately from Heaven with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome extraordinary Teſtimony to evince the Truth of it. The im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate Miſſion which theſe men pretend to, requires an extraordinary
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:35221:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Teſtimony, or no man in his right Wits can believe or aſſent to its Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, or eſteem it for any thing but mere Deluſion, or Uſurpation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cretian</hi> Church muſt be allowed to be framed according to <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>les</hi> (I keep to this Gentlemans term) in that Church, St. <hi>Paul</hi> appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Titus</hi> to Ordain Elders in every City; none in the <hi>Scriptural Churches</hi> (as this Gent Phraſes it) was to enter upon the Paſtoral, or Prieſtly Office, without Epiſcopal Ordination. Our bleſſed Saviour ſaith, <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> 10.1. <hi>Verily I ſay unto you, he that entreth not by the door into the Sheep ſold, but climbeth ſome other way, the ſame is a Thieſ and a Robber:</hi> Not entring in at the <hi>Door</hi> ſignifies, entring without that Authority which the Author of our Religion hath Ordained in his Church; without this Miſſion, (<hi>i. e.</hi> Epiſcopal Ordination) no man hath Authority to Preach the Goſpel, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter Sacraments, or exerciſe any thing appropriate to the Prieſtly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice; unleſs theſe men can manifeſt that they have this Miſſion, they are ſo far from being a <hi>Scriptural Church,</hi> that our bleſſed Saviour pronounc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth them to be <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers.</hi> By this account of the Frame of their Church (ſuppoſing, but not granting it to be a Church) it appears to have no Foundation of a <hi>Scriptural Church,</hi> but on the contrary is Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly Scripture.</p>
            <p>Let it now be examined whether All they impoſe as Terms of Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, be by <hi>expreſs Rules in Scripture?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then I deſire they'l inform us, where did our bleſſed Saviour, or his Apoſtles appoint the firſt day of the Week for Celebration of the Public Worſhip?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What precept have they in Scripture for chooſing a Text as is now uſed to Preach upon, or the erection of a Pulpit?</p>
            <p n="3">3. What Divine Command have your Brethren for the Form of Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lic Penance, the Stool of Repentance, impoſed by the Kirk of <hi>Scotland</hi> and the Presbyterians in <hi>England?</hi> Theſe are I ſuppoſe, Terms of Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with you; I am not diſputing againſt the Practice of theſe things, but hence it appears how unreaſonable and falſe, that Principle you ſo much contend for is, to wit; that nothing is to be done about the Worſhip and Service of God, without Rules and expreſs Command in the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But I farther demand of you,</p>
            <p n="4">4. What Divine Warrant, or where in Scripture did your Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors find thoſe three ſignificant Ceremonies, impoſed without the Regal Authority, at the taking the <hi>Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> which you at this day juſtifie? Firſt the Takers muſt be uncovered. <hi>2ly,</hi> they
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:35221:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>muſt ſtand up. <hi>3ly,</hi> The right hand muſt be lifted up bare; all theſe Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies in this Religious Solemnity, ſignifying the Submiſſion and Aſſent of the parties to that Rebellious Covenant, were Inſtituted by the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians.</p>
            <p>In his 37 p. he ſays, <hi>We deſire the Rules of the Goſpel may be carefully looked into, and a model of Government and Worſhip taken from thence, ſuch as may be likely to anſwer the great ends of Church Societies,</hi> &amp;c. Here's our <hi>Government and Worſhip</hi> ſuppoſed to be inconſiſtent with <hi>the Rules of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel;</hi> thence a neceſſity of Reformation; and who can deny ſo fair an Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer? <hi>The Model</hi> theſe good men will ſet up, ſhall be a <hi>Model for Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Worſhip</hi> (not like our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſcriptural Church,</hi> but) taken from <hi>the Rules of the Goſpel.</hi> But here its demanded.</p>
            <p n="5">5. What Rule or Command is there in all the Sacred Scriptures, for private and Unauthorized perſons, ſuch as theſe men are, under pretence of Reformation, to ſupplant a Catholic Church, truly Reformed in <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment and Worſhip,</hi> to primitive purity (as I have ſhewed) and eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all the Authority that can be had on Earth from God or Man? Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceited men! Think ye that thoſe Pious Martyrs who Reformed our Church inſpected not <hi>the Rules of the Goſpel</hi> as carefully and Conſcienciouſly as you? and are not the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat ends of Church Society anſwered,</hi> (viz.) the Chriſtian Faith truly profeſſed and maintained; the Holy Sacraments duly admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred, and ſuch an Unity and Chriſtian Charity obſerved and practiced ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Rules of the Goſpel in our Church, as exactly and amply as in any Church on this ſide Heaven?</p>
            <p>His next words in p. 38. are, <hi>That nothing may be impoſed but what is either expresſly commanded; or has a natural and proper tendency to promote that which is ſo,</hi> &amp;c. This is Anſwered before.</p>
            <p>He ſaith farther; <hi>Then would the Worſhip and Service of God appear like itſelf, Rational, Grave and Majeſtical, becoming reaſonable Creatures,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Here are all men to be perſwaded, that the Worſhip and Service in their Conventicles is eminently more <hi>Rational, Grave and Majeſtic</hi> than in our Churches. The truth of this will beſt appear from their practice.</p>
            <p>None of their Addreſſes to K. <hi>James</hi> the ſecond were preſented, 'till the Compoſure and Form thereof, was deliberated and well weighed by more than One, by the whole Claſſis of a County: The Preacher ſaith, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Be not raſh with thy Mouth, and let not thine Heart be haſty to utter any thing before God,</hi> &amp;c. But they, in their Conventicles, Addreſs the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of Heaven, they ruſh upon and approach his preſence, with the raſh and Sudden thoughts of one ſingle perſon, with a Prayer newly Coined, but whether Sterling; true, according to Standard, being never tryed, is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:35221:23"/>uncertain, for the people know it not, nor the Orator, till it be out; they ſhew'd more Fear and Reverence to an earthly King, than they dayly do to God Almighty. Is this Rational? Is this Grave?</p>
            <p>In their Conventicles, at the reading the Holy Scriptures, among which the Pſalms, conſiſting of the higheſt ſtrains of Devotion, they Sit or Loll, and are covered; is this <hi>Grave and Majeſtic?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When the Miniſter (as they call him) offer up his (raſh and unconſider'd) Prayers to God, the People are in confuſed, and irreverend poſtures, as if there were ſome unconcern'd and trivial thing in hand; is this <hi>Grave and Majeſtical?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He who Adminiſters in their Divine Worſhip (as they call it) has no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Habit than what is due to, and becomes a Tradeſman, or any other Layic in the Congregation (and indeed therein they are very modeſt; the Miniſter for the moſt part having no more claim to Prieſtly Garments than his Auditors) is this <hi>Grave and Majeſtic?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, theſe men are ſo humorſome, that what is <hi>Rational</hi> they condemn as Senceleſs; what is <hi>Grave and Majeſtical,</hi> they condemn for Superſtition; and on the contrary, what is Rude, Irreverend and Foppiſh, they eſteem as <hi>Rational, Grave and Majeſtical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By this time it is very evident, that the Diſſenters in <hi>England</hi> do Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from a Church, wherein there is (to uſe Mr. <hi>H-ry</hi>'s words) not any thing amiſs; <hi>i. e.</hi> not any thing that can give any juſt occaſion to Separate from her; and that the Communion (for I cannot call it a Church) or <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety</hi> they joyn themſelves to, is ſo far from being better, that in many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects which I have mentioned, it is ſo much worſe, that its an abſurdity to compare them.</p>
            <p>The Inference then, drawn by Mr. <hi>H-ry</hi> from his own Propoſition is clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt them,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>H-ry p.</hi> 19.</note> that their <hi>Separation from our Church</hi> is clearly <hi>for Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſake,</hi> and is neceſſarily an <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncharitable Alienation of Affection,</hi> and is conſequently <hi>Schiſmatical.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having alſo conſidered my Authors Notion of Schiſm; to wit,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>p.</hi> 37.</note> 
               <hi>for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons wilfully to with-draw themſelves from ſuch particular Churches, as are fram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to Scripture Rules, and impoſe no new or needleſs Terms, is to act Schiſmatically, becauſe ſuch wilful Separation when no cauſe is given, cannot be without breach of Charity with our fellow-Chriſtians, which is the Scripture Notion of Schiſm.</hi> Having ſhewed, that our Church is truly framed ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to <hi>Scripture Rules,</hi> and that ſhe impoſeth neither <hi>New</hi> nor <hi>needleſs Terms;</hi> this Inference of his, is neceſſarily againſt them too, viz. <hi>That the wilfull with-drawing</hi> of theſe men <hi>from ſuch a particular Church</hi> as our Church is, <hi>is to act Schiſmatically,</hi> &amp;c. If any thing would prevail upon
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:35221:24"/>the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>inacy of theſe men, here is conviction from their own Reaſoning.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> fair dealing with Mr. <hi>H-ry</hi> at this time, will make an Attone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>mer Omiſſion, and allay my Adverſaries bitter thoughts againſt me.</p>
            <p>In my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> paper, p. 7. I inſtanced the Authoritys of <hi>Ienatius, Iren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ian,</hi> and <hi>A <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> who were all Biſhops and Mattyrs, and agree, T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey then Biſhops and Presbyters appointed &amp; ſet ever them; and to S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>parate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to ſet up diſtinct Conventicles, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>. Is not by this underſtood <hi>di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty or Separation of Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> is not this properly Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſm? Yet for this my aſſirmati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he does in his 45 p. peremptorily charge me (and conſequently thoſe Pious Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yrs) with giving St. <hi>Paul</hi> the Lye. It St. <hi>Paul</hi> condemn'd the <hi>Corinthians</hi> for admiring, and barely pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ing one Miniſter before ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, of Schiſm; ſhall that far greater and blacker Crime, the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſaking, and Separating from them, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o which the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> were not then arriv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) be excluded from Schiſm? Shall a cut in the Arm be truly call'd Schiſm or Schiſſure; and ſhall not the lopping off, and Separating the Arm from the Body, (which is the Diſſenters Caſe) be accounted ſo? Wherein do I give St. <hi>Paul</hi> the lye? This Gent. is a topping Accuſer.</p>
            <p>The reſt of his Book contains chiefly, Bitter Invectives, and Scurrilous Reflections; at his bitter reviling of me, I wonder not; But ſtand amaz'd at his hardyneſs, and indeed horrid and groſs Impiety, with ſo much Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom and Malice, to take into Royal Sepulchers, and render our Four Proteſtant Monarchs Infamous; ſee his p. 61. (of K. <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> he ſaith) <hi>not to be paralell'd in Story.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi>'s Reign, our Church was again Reform'd; all the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations and Superſtitions, which by a long ſeries of time, the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had introduced into the Church, and Conſecrated with the Title of the <hi>Did Religion,</hi> aboliſhed; the ineſtimable Bleſſing of the truly An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Catho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Religion, revived and eſtabliſhed; this Religious Queen, and all thoſe pious Prelates, to whom under God, the praiſe of all that Glorious work was due, eſcape no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> his malice, but in one breath blackens and defames them all; theſe are his words in p. 75. <hi>That great Princeſs had ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>thing of the Sire in her, and there wanted not Prelatic breath to blow the Spark into a Flame.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Univerſal Fame this Great Princeſs had for Wiſdom and Piety; the Turbu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en Humor, and Inſolent behaviour of the Diſſenters towards Her, you have an account of, in Biſh. <hi>Barnet's A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dgment,</hi> &amp;c. the <hi>4th</hi> Book, p. 381. Now notwithſtanding, that this man ſaith in his <hi>2d</hi> p. <q>that Penal Laws had a quite contrary effect; and in his <hi>3d</hi> p. that they
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:35221:24"/>have not hitherto brought Proteſtants to an exact Uniformity;</q> this Queen in the year 1592, made Penal Laws, which being Vigorouſly Executed, contrary to his maxims, had the good <hi>effects and proper ends</hi> for which they were made; ſuppreſt the Ring-leaders, and put an end to their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venticles, and brought ſo many of them to Conformity, that during Her reign afterwards, ſhe had no more diſturbances from them; and this I ſuppoſe to be the chief incentive of this Male-contents diſpleaſure againſt this Great and Matchleſs Princeſs.</p>
            <p>In his 56 p. concerning K. <hi>James</hi> the firſt, he ſaith: <hi>For when King</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Englands <hi>Throne, the Prelatic Party dreading leaſt the Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>tans <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> great a ſhare in his Favours, upon the account of his Ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Scottiſh Nobility and Miniſtry might have upon hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Studies to creat a prejudice againſt them; and f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ing no <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> take with him, as the extending of his Authority, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rogative,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>They Flatt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red the Ambition and Vices of that Prince, and there<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made him intirely their own.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To ſhew how falſe this Affirmation is, I will here ſet down the Opinion which that Learned and Judicious Prince, had of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Puritans, from a long experience; Publiſhed and declared in Print at <hi>Edinborough,</hi> ſome years before his Acceſſion to the Throne of <hi>England.</hi> He calls the Presbyterian Government, <hi>animagined Dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cracy;</hi> and ſaith,<note place="margin">ΒΑΖ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>Ι<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ΛΙΚΟΝ Δ ΩΡΟΝ</note> 
               <q>That they fed themſelves with the hope to become <hi>Tribuni Plebis;</hi> and ſo in a popular Government, by leading the people by the Noſe, to bear the ſway of all the Rule, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>And a little farther:</hi>
               <note place="margin">p. 39. p. 41. p. 42.</note> 
               <q>Take heed therfore my Son, to ſuch Puritans, very peſts in the Church and Common-weal; whom no deſerts can oblige, neither Oaths not Promiſes bind; breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing but Sedition and Calumnies; aſpiring without Meaſure, rayling without Reaſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </q> 
               <hi>And a little farther, after comparing them to</hi> Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> land, or Border-Thieves for ingratitude, Lying and Perjuries, <hi>he ſaith;</hi> 
               <q>And ſuffer not the Principals of them to brook your Land, if you like to ſit at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſt: except ye would keep them for trying your Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, as <hi>Secrates</hi> did an evil Wife.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Now had this man the leaſt grain of Shame or Modeſty, common to Human Nature, he would never have expoſed himſelf to ſo plain and known a c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tradiction: <hi>That the Engliſh Prelates ſlatter'd</hi> him into an ill Opinion <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the Plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ans,</hi> is ſo far from being true, that it was founded upon his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. Experience, and Publiſhed long before he had any converſe with the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gliſh Prelates.</hi> And that he ſhould accuſe that King of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition and Vices,</hi> who was ſo eminently Famous for Piety and Virtue, is horridly wicked. Here is great Reaſon for this man to conceal his name.</p>
            <pb n="44" facs="tcp:35221:25"/>
            <p>Againſt K. <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, he maſters up a Roll of all the hainous Crime the can Imagin, which I could anſwer particularly, but for his Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication from this man's malicious Calumny; it is ſufficient to refer the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Rolls and Acts of Parliament (of which he mentions not a word) and all other Tranſactions which paſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in his time, not yet out of mem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ry. What did that <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> ask, which He did not grant, except the Tower of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>a? which becauſe he thought it too <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to Separate from the Monarchy, they Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d by Violence: Never was a King to food <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> a Parliament (witneſs His paſſing the Bill for not Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ving them without their co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ert) and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver were there ſuch ungrateful returns; He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the Peace &amp; Tranquility of the Nation, and they were for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ying it into Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vulſions and Rebellion: He was for preſerving and mainta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing the Church, in all Her Ancient juſt Eſtabliſhed Rights, and they for de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>roying both Her and Him. They indeed contriv'd and gave him Op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ies, to his <hi>Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Fame,</hi> to ſhew how eminently the Grace of God was in him; never did any Prince, ſince the Prince of Peace, ſhew more Catiſtian Courage, Patience, Meckneſs, and Hamili<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, even to the Admiration and Aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of His moſt Barbarous and Cruel Enemies. Now whileſt this man contracts the guilt of the Murder of this Royal Martyr, by juſtifying all thoſe irre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ular and Horrid proceedings of the Presbyterians which brought it about, I do heartily with all good men keep the Anniverſary Faſt and pray with our Church, that His memory may be ever bleſſed among us: and that this Land may be freed from the Vengeance of his blood <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Here is Sufficient reaſon for this man to conceal his name.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Violation of Promiſes,</hi> which in that 61. <hi>pa.</hi> he charges upon <hi>the Church and Court party</hi> upon the Reſtauration, can be nothing elſe but Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n and Forgery, to prove which, greater Evidence cannot be for any thing, than the Acts of that Parliament which K <hi>Charles</hi> the <hi>2d</hi> immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately called; upon whom, without Reſerve he rely'd, not only to reform and forgive all the Irregularities, but to renew the very Foundations, and to R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſtabliſh the Government of Church and State; both which, were O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rturned and laid in Rubbiſh, by an Unnatural Rebellion, fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>d and carryed on, by the Presbyterians and their Adhaerents, (Witneſs their Illuſtrious <hi>Solemn League and Covenant</hi>) and accor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>l all things were by that Parliament Re-eſtabliſhed and co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>firmed, to the ſatisfaction o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Nation in General; and this was the Conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mation of that Treaty at <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> Where now is the Violation of Promiſes? The and<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>us <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flections of this man, Loaden with ſo much Malice, againſt our Four Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Monarchs; is rather the Character of a Jeſuit, than of any other
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:35221:25"/>Society, it is ſo like them. This man Conceals his Name, and let it be ſo; <hi>for the Name of the Wicked ſhall rot,</hi> Prov. 10. I will cloſe this with the complaint of the Royal Prophet; <hi>What ſhall be done unto thee O thou falſe tongue.</hi> Pſal. 10.7.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But Bleſſed be God,</hi> ſays he in <hi>pa.</hi> 62. <hi>We have a King upon the Throne, that underſtands, and loves the tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Intereſt of</hi> England, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is well He is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Throne, and God gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt him long to be ſo; But who can account <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mens praiſes to a King on the Throne, for any thing but Flattery and Hypocriſy, that knows five years are not yet expir'd, ſince theſe men uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rſally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ater's King <hi>Jame<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>'s far beyond this, in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gyties to him, when on the Throne. But would you know the true Intereſt o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>En<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nd</hi>? Learn of him who infalibly underſtood it, He ſaith, <hi>That a Kingdom divided againſt it ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f cannot ſtand.</hi> Mar. 3 24. Unity in Religion being the Sureſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>work, and the moſt approved preſervative of a Kingdom from dividing, is certainly the <hi>trueſt Intereſt</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Diſſenters then, who creat Diviſions, making Parties and Factions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout matters not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſential to Religion, according to our bleſſed Saviour's Maxim, neither underſtand nor love the true Intereſt of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In his 66. p. he ſaith, <hi>We hold Communion with you in all that's neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y, either to the Being or Welfare of a Church, and by your unneceſſary Trifles, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> break with us, and not we with you, if any breach there be.</hi> To which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> anſwer.</p>
            <p>To the Being of a Church, it is neceſſary that the Government be of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine Inſtitution, which I have ſhew'd to be Epiſcopacy; And that the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers be United in a peaceable Subjection to the Government, is abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> neceſſary to the Being and Welfare of a Church; for without this, not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ly the Peace, which is the Welfare, but the very Being of a Church, muſt be Diſſolved and Swallowed up in Diviſion and Confuſion. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our ſetting up a Government Diſtinct and Oppoſit to the Ancient Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Eſtabliſhed in the Church, than which the bleſſed Saints and Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rs of old knew no other, and under pretence of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nneceſſary Trifles,</hi> (as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ou call 'em) to withdraw all Obedience and Subjection, which is plainly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtructive, not only to the Welfare, but the very <hi>Being</hi> of a Church, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et ſo confidently to affirm, you hold Communion with us in all that's ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſſary thereunto, is to impoſe upon our very Senſes; and to believe it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere to degenerate into Senſleſs Brutes.</p>
            <p>But alaſs! ſhould the Church condeſcend to gratifie your Humor, ſtrip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Prieſt of his Habit, the Emblem of Innocency, the Colour o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Robes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> St. <hi>John</hi>'s Viſion, and in which all the Meſſengers from Heaven appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>? Should ſhe for your ſake, abandon the Sign of the Croſs, ſo anciently
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:35221:26"/>uſed in all Catholic Churches? Should ſhe yield to rob her Members of their Ancient Right; by Cancelling and Oblitterating the Liturgy, which for Matter and Order how uſeful and neceſſary for Public Devotion, let it ſelf Teſtifie? And inſtead thereof allow Extemporary Prayers, which, what crude and indigeſted matter for the moſt part they are, we have heard and know; and which cannot poſſibly without the Stamp of Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (which they are not capable of) or be made appear to be the dictates of the Spirit, thô programed before Ten thouſand people, bear the Title of Public or Common P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayers. Should the prohibit Kneeling, and enjoyn us like Crowns and B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>s, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> we Celebrate the Commemora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Death and P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ion of our bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Redeg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er in the E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>chariſt? Should ſhe forbid bowing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> my De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tion, at the ſaving name of J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us, &amp; paying Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>al Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tion to God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, which the very light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teacheth? And ſhould ſhe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> which you a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ingly call Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fles? Alas! She muſt betray<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er Tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> level the Prieſt-ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d ſhe muſt Surrender and part with the Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tabli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hed by Divine Inſtitution, or you will never be fatis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>yed: this is evident in the whole ſtrain of your Book, and is the avowed and Darling Principle of all Diſſenters, of what perſwaſion ſoever; were their Diviſions more numerous than the points in the Compaſs, yet they will all agree and Center in this, <hi>viz.</hi> the Expulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Dioceſan Biſhops from the Government of the Church: not conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they contend and ſtrive againſt the Ordinance of God, <hi>the Care and Charge of all the Churches,</hi> being intruſted and committed to them; and who thrô all Ages from the Apoſtles, as faithful Over-ſeers of the Church of God, have handed down, and delivered to us, the Holy Scriptures, the Articles of Faith, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he holy Sacraments, and all that's Sacred, and condu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cive to Holineſs, Unity and Charity here, and to that future happy Eſtate of perfect Holineſs and Unity Eternal hereafter. Ungrateful men! is their Extirpation and Deſtruction a meet reward for conveying to us ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable Ble<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſings? Are ye the meek Servants of the meek and Holy Jeſus, who m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Rebel againſt them that bear his Authority? Can ye be the Diſciples of Chriſt, who abjure and declare againſt his Ambaſſadors? Or can ye be e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ed the Subjects of the Prince of Peace, who ſow the Seeds of Contention, and are the Authors of Separation, of Diviſion and Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in the Church of God? No, no, He hath formded our Religion in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, in Peace and Obedience; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one can be his Diſciple, who is a viol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>tian Charity, making no Conſcience (under pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ence) to diſturb the Peace, and diſſolve the Unity of the Church, not only by diſobeying the Governors thereof, in thoſe things which our Savior having leſt indifferent, hath left in their Power to impoſe
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:35221:26"/>and Command; but by deſpiſing them, and endeavouring their utter Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirpation. <hi>As the Tree is known by its Fruit,</hi> ſo are you by your Works; If any have been Guilty of Schiſm ever ſince the Aſcention, or can be till the Second Advent of our Lord, our Diſſenters are manifeſtly ſo. And as the Confute of the Church, judicially pronounced againſt Scandalous, Lend, and diſorderly perſons, excludes them from the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> calls, <hi>deliv ring up unto Satan.</hi> So theſe Diſſenters,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>v.</hi> 5. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1. <hi>v.</hi> 20.</note> by deſpiſing and renouncing the Government of the Church, by withdraw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Separating themſelves from Communion with her, involve and hurry themſelves wilfully, into the ſame State and Condition with thoſe, who by judicial Sentence are put out of the Congregation of Chriſt's Flock; how deplorable ſoever it is to be ſo, this is the true ſtate of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe of all who as our Diſſenters, are guilty of Criminous Schiſm, they exclude them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves from the <hi>Catholic Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Holy Scriptures abound with Remedies againſt this, but I will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to mind them only of theſe, preſcribed by St. <hi>Paul.</hi> The firſt is; <hi>Mind not high things, but condeſcend to men of low Eſtate; be not Wiſe in your own conceits.</hi> Now not to ſubmit in things Indifferent,<note place="margin">Rom. <hi>12.</hi> v. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> which being Commanded by our Lawful Governors, are made a Duty, is very contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this Command of <hi>condeſcending to men of low Eſtate.</hi> And they muſt be <hi>Wiſe in</hi> their <hi>own Conceits,</hi> who occaſion the breach of Charity and U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, by preſerring and obſtinately contending for their own private Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, againſt the deliberate and United Councils and Decrees of their Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riors, in thoſe things wherein the Eſſentials of Religion are not the leaſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd. The next is, <hi>Follow Peace with all men, and Holineſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. <hi>12.</hi> v. <hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>without which, no man ſhall ſee the Lord;</hi> Holineſs is but pretence, and if I may call it ſo, mere Pageantry in Religion, in thoſe who do not <hi>follow Peace with all men,</hi> much more in them who will not be at Peace with their Lawful Spiritual Governors; for he who hath not Peace as well as Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhall never ſee God. And now more full of Charitable deſires, than hope of the Conviction of theſe men to Chriſtian Peace and Unity, with a Reſolution never to give them any more trouble of this kind; as I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with our Saviours Command, and Bleſſed Legacy of Peace, ſo I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Exhortation; <hi>Be of one mind, live in Peace,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13 <hi>v.</hi> 11.</note> 
               <hi>and the God of Peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
